Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 102-106, September 2007

Prediction of the Exposure to 1763MHz Radiofrequency Radiation Based on Gene Expression Patterns

Min Su Lee’, Tai-Qin Huang^, Jeong-Sun Seo^ and Woong-Yang Park^*

’Biointelligence Laboratory, School of Computer Science and Engineering, ^ILCHUN Genomic Medicine Institute, MRC and Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, College of Medicine, Seoul National University, Seoul 110-799, Korea

Abstract

Radiofrequency (RF) radiation at the frequency of mobile phones has been not reported to induce cellular responses in in vitro and in vivo models. We exposed HEI-OC1, conditionally-immortalized mouse auditory cells, to RF radiation to characterize cellular responses to 1763 MHz RF radiation. While we could not detect any differences

upon RF exposure, whole-genome expression profiling might provide the most sensitive method to find the molecular responses to RF radiation. HEI-OC1 cells were exposed to 1763 MHz RF radiation at an average specific absorption rate (SAR) of 20 W/kg for 24 hr and harvested after 5 hr of recovery (R5), alongside sham-exposed samples (S5). From the whole-genome profiles of mouse neurons, we selected 9 differentially-expressed genes between the S5 and R5 groups using information gain-based recursive feature elimination procedure. Based on support vector machine (SVM), we designed a prediction model using the 9 genes to discriminate the two groups. Our prediction model could predict the target class without any error. From these results, we developed a prediction model using biomarkers to determine the RF radiation exposure in mouse auditory cells with perfect accuracy, which may need validation in in vivo RF-exposure models.

Keywords: support vector machine, prediction, microarray, radiofrequency radiation, auditory cell

Introduction

RF radiation does not transfer high enough energy to break the covalent bonds of macromolecules, but these

‘Corresponding author; E-mail wypark@snu.ac.kr

Tel +82-2-740-8241, Fax +82-2-744-4534 Accepted 15 August 2007

low energy stimuli might be enough to induce molecular responses such as cell proliferation or cell death (Moulder etal., 1999). While RF radiation itself can not mediate direct effects on DNA and proteins, it can trigger signaling pathways through changes in ionic distribution or membrane fluidity. In addition, the interactions between genes and RF radiation can lower the threshold of physiological changes,

including various pathological conditions.

The brain is the most important target tissue to study the biological effect of RF radiation in mobile phone users (Harden et ai., 1999). There was a report on theincrease in tumors ipsilateral to the side of the head on which

subjects recalled phone use (Inskip etal., 1999), but this was not substantiated by other studies (Muscat et al., 2000). RF radiation exposure to rat headsdid not affect the

incidence, malignancy, volume, multiplicity, latency, or fatality associated with any kind of neurogenic tumor (Zook and Simmens, 2006).

Alteration of cognitive and physiological functions of brains upon exposure to mobile phone-frequency RF radiation has been reported by several electrophysiological

studies (Curcio etal., 2005). In summary, RF exposure can induce measurable changes in human brain electrical activity, particularly in the alpha frequency band (8-13 Hz)

over posterior regions of the scalp. In addition, rats exposed to RF showed neuronal damage in the cortex, hippocampus, and basal ganglia (Salford etal., 2003). However, this work was not reproduced by others (Joubert etal., 2007), and

there are a number of points to consider regarding whether RF radiation can affect the human brain and its subsequent output in the form of cognition and behavior.

Gene expression profiling with microarrays can provide

valuable information on the characteristics of certain

physiological and pathological conditions. For example, gene expression profiles of-irradiated Jurkat cells showed p53-independent activation of the NF-B pathway (Park ef al., 2002). In the case of RF radiation, the expression patterns of HL-60 cells exposed to 2.45 GHz RF radiation were examined to select genes related to RF radiation (Lee etal., 2005b). We have used HEI-OC1 mouse auditory cells to find biomarkers related to RF radiation-exposure, and have developed prediction models of RF-exposure using support vector machine (SVM) algorithms (Vapnik,

1998) with selected biomarkers based on the Weka

environment (Witten and Frank, 2005).

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Materials and Methods

Cell culture

Conditionally-immortalized HEI-OC1 auditory cells were kindly provided by Dr. Kalinec (House Ear Institute, Los Angeles, CA, USA). Cells were cultured under permissive conditions (33°C 10% CO2) in high-glucose Dulbecco's Modified Eagle's Medium (DMEM; GIBCO/BRL, Gaithers¬ burg, Md., USA) containing 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum (FBS, GIBCO/BRL) and 50 U/mL gamma¬ interferon (Gemzyme, Cambridge, MA, USA) as previously described (Jat, 1991).

RF exposure system

The exposure system specifically designed for this study was reported previously by Lee eta/, in our laboratory (Lee eta/., 2006). For the PCS exposure system, a real CDMA signal at 1762.5 MHz was applied.

Cells were exposed to 1763 MHz RF radiation in 100 mm Petri dishes containing 18 mL of medium. The exposure system was then warmed up for 30 min to equilibrate it before exposure of RF. RF radiation exposure was conducted at

SAR values of 20 W/kg. During exposure, the temperature inside the chamber was maintained at 33+0.2°C by circulating water within the cavity. After an exposure of 24 or 48 hr, the cells were transferred to a cell culture incubator for 5 hr and then harvested. For sham exposure, cells were incubated in the RF radiation device, but were not exposed to RF radiation.

RF-exposure design

HEI-OC1 mouse auditory cells were exposed to 20 W/kg of 1763 MHz RF radiation for 24 hr, and then cells were incubated for 5 hr to recover from acute responses (R5 group). Sham-exposed cells were harvestedin parallel (S5 group). We repeated these sets of experiment threetimes to collect biological triplicates for every sample.

RNA extraction and microarray

Samples in each group were harvested, and their total RNA was extracted by dissolving cells in Trizol (Sigma). After fractions containing the RNA were collected, total RNA was purified using Qiagen RNeasy columns. The array used in this experiment was the Applied Biosystems 1700 full genome expression mouse microarray,which includes 32,000 mouse genes from the public and Celera databases

(http://www.pantherdb.org/).

Data analysis

Fluorescence intensity was processed and measured

Prediction of the Exposure to Radiofrequency Radiation 103

using the Applied Biosystems 1700 Chemiluminescent Microarray Analyzer. Intensity data were imported to an in-house microarray database. The overall procedure for constructing a prediction model to discriminate the exposure of RF radiation using the microarray data is shown in Fig. 1.

To perform reliable microarray data analysis, some probes were filtered out based on the following 3-step gene-filtering process. Firstly, control genes were excluded after checking their expression level. Then, unreliable inten¬

sities of probes were excluded based on flag information.

Finally, reliable probes, whose ratio of signal-to-noise

intensity (S/N) was more than 3 in 50% or more of the total samples, were used to construct a prediction model. The threshold of the S/N ratio was derived from a rigorous

quality control test by Applied Biosystems that showed that if the S/N of a probe is more than 3, then the signal intensity of the probe is reliable with 99.9% confidence. As a result, 15,040 probes were left.

Quantile normalization was applied to remove systematic variance. Quantile normalization is a simple yet powerful method to normalize across arrays by making the distribution of probe intensities for each array in a set of arrays the same, and it reduces the variance slightly better than Lowess normalization (Bolstadl eta/., 2003).

Microarray Dataset

Prediction model

with optimal subset of genes

Fig. 1. Analysis procedure for constructing a prediction model

-----------------------------------------------------Page 2-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
104 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 102-106, September 2007

We sorted genes according to the significance of changes in gene expression levels between the two groups using information gain. Information gain is a measure of the effectiveness of a feature in classifying the

training data (Mitchell, 1997). Given entropy Ehtropy(S)

as a measure of the impurity in a training data, information gain IG(^S, F} of a feature F relative to a collection of samples S is the expected reduction in entropy caused by partitioning the samples according to this feature. Hence,

the information gain can be defined as the difference between the entropy of the original collection S and the expected value of the entropy after s is partitioned using

feature F as follows:

/G(5, F) = Entropy(S) - X W £^ntropy(S^)

veFb/ue(F) ?

where Fa/ue(F’)is the set of all possible values for feature F, and is the subset of 5 for which feature Fhas

value o.

To construct an optimal classification model to predict the

exposure to RF radiation with a minimal set of biomarkers, we adopted a recursive feature elimination (RFE) procedure (Furlanello, etal. 2(X)3, Guyon, etal. 21X12) based on information gain and a support vector machine (SVM) algorithm (Vapnik, V.N., 1998). The RFE procedure recursivelyremoves

the features that cause the minimum variation with support vector machines (Guyon etal. 2002). SVMs have exhibited superb performance in binary classification tasks that search for a hyperplane that separates two classes of data with the largest margin between the hyperplane and the point closest to it. At each model building step in RFE, a

classifier and a ranked gene set are constructed and evaluated, and a single feature is eliminated at each step. Hence,the basic RFE procedure with SVM has high computational cost. To speed up the RFE-SVM procedure, we used the information gain-based RFE procedure to obtain an optimal gene subset for predicting the exposure of RF radiation. Gene selection with RFE procedures based on information gaineliminates gene redundancy effectively and yields better and more compact gene subsets. We constructed prediction models with selected gene subsets using a sequential minimal optimization

F[0..N-l]: a feature set with N features that is sorted by information gain in decreasing order

accuracy(i):

accuracy

prediction model

based on

SVM with F[0..

•i] gene set

low = 0

high = N-1

value = accuracy(N-l)

IG_RFE_SVM(F[0...N-l], value, low, high) {

if (high low)

return F[0...N-l] and value

mid - (low + high) / 2

value_2 = accuracy(mid)

if (value_2 > value)

return IG_RFE_SVM(F[0...mid], value_2, low, mid)

else (value_2 < value)

return IG_REF_SVM(F[0...high], value, mid, high)

Fig. 2. Pseudo-code of information gain-based recursive feature elimination procedure with SVM

-----------------------------------------------------Page 3-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Prediction of the Exposure to Radiofrequency Radiation 105

Table 1. List of selected genes derived by information gain-based RFE with SVM

algorithm with a logistic regression model and RBF kernel for training a support vector classifier (Platt, J., 1998) based on the Weka environment (Witten and Frank, 2005). We estimated the prediction error of the model with

leave-one-out cross-validation (LOOCV) (Tan, ef al., 2005). Specifically, if the number of samples is n, LOOCV

means that the cross-validation procedure is run n times, each time using one of the samples as the test set and the others as training sets. LOOCV had the advantage of utilizing as much data as possible for training. In addition, the test sets were mutually exclusive, and they effectively covered the entire dataset. Also, LOOCV seems to offer a chance of squeezing the maximum out of a small dataset and obtaining as accurate an estimate as possible (Tan,

efa/.,2005).

Results and Discussion

RF exposure to HEI-OC1 mouse auditory cells

Upon exposure to 1763 MHz RF radiation, HEI-OC1 mouse auditory cells did not show any change in cell morphology or growth (unpublished data). We kept the cells in a CO2 incubator while cells were exposed to RF radiation. RF radiation can produce heat in the culture media, but isothermal water at 37°C circulated continuously at the bottom of the chamber throughout the experiment. Because

we kept the chamber inside a CO2 incubator, cells were

completely shielded from any electromagnetic field radiation generated from other electronic sources. For the sham group, we assembled the exact same experimental setup as in the RF exposure without applying the current.

Information gain-based recursive feature elimination

with SVM

We identified a discriminative and compact gene subset for predicting the exposure of RF radiation according to the

following procedure. Firstly, genes were sorted by their information gain score. Then using RFE with SVM based on a binary search algorithm, we searched for the gene subset with the highest accuracy and minimal size. Specifically, a binary search algorithm finds the median element g„ in a sorted gene set, compares the prediction accuracy of the top n genes to the one that was previously computed based on the SVM algorithm, and determines if the prediction accuracy is greater than, less than, or equal to the previously-computed one, iteratively. The pseudo¬ code of the information gain-based recursive feature elimination procedure with SVM is shown in Fig.2. By adopting information gain-based RFE with SVM in a divide-and-conquer approach, we could effectively eliminate chunks of uninteresting genes and identify 9 genes with perfect classification accuracy. We briefly summarize information about the 9 genes in Table 1.

Acknowledgements

This work was supported by the IT R&D program of MIC/ IITA [2007-F-043-01, Study on Diagnosis and Protection Technology based on EM].

References

Bolstad, B.M., Irizarry R.A., Astrand, M., and Speed, T.P. (2003). A comparison of normalization methods for high density oligonucleotide array data based on bias and variance. Bioinformatics 19, 185-193.

Curcio, G., Ferrara, M., Moroni, F., D'lnzeo, G., Bertini, M.,

and De Gennaro, L. (2005). Is the brain influenced by a phone call? An EEG study of resting wakefulness. Neurosci Res. 53, 265-270.

Furlanello, C., Serafini, M, Merler, S., and Jurrran, G (2003). Entropy¬ based gene ranking without selection bias for the predictive classification of rricroarray data. BMC Bioinformatics, 4, 54.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 4-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
106 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 102-106, September 2007

Guyon, I., Weston, J., Barnhill, B., and Vapnik, V. (2002). Gene Selection for Cancer Classification using Support Vector Machines. Machine Learning 46, 389-422.

Harden, L., Nasman, A., Pahlson, A., Hallquist, A., and Mild,

K.H. (1999). Use of cellular telephones and the risk of brain tumours: a case control study, int J Oncoiogy 15,113-116.

Inskip, P.D., Tarone, R.E., Hatch, E.E., Wilcosky, T.C., Shapiro, W.R., Selker, R.G., Fine, H.A., Black, P.M., Loeffler, J.S., and Linet, M.S. (2001). Cellular-telephone

use and brain tumors. New Engiand Journai of Medicine 344, 79-86.

Jat, P.S., Noble, M.D., Ataliotis, P., Tanaka, Y., Yannoutsos, N., Larsen, L, Kioussis, D. (1991). Direct derivation of

conditionally immortal cell lines from an H-2Kb-tsA58 transgenic mouse. Proc. Nati. Acad. Sci. USA 88,5096-5100.

Joubert, V., Leveque, P., Cueille, M., Bourthoumieu, S., and Yardin, C. (2007). No apoptosis is induced in rat cortical neurons exposed to GSM phone fields. Bioeiectromagnetics 28, 115-121.

Lee, J.S., Huang, T.Q., Kim, T.H., Kim, J.Y., Kim, H.J., Pack, J.K., and Seo, J.S. (2006). Radiofrequency radiation does not induce stress response in human T-lymphocytes and

rat primary astrocytes. Bioeiectromagnetics. 27, 578-88. Lee, S., Johnson, D., Dunbar, K., Dong, H., Ge, X., Kim, Y.C., Wing, C., Jayathilaka, N., Emmanuel, N., Zhou, C.Q., Gerber, H.L., Tseng, C.C., and Wang, S.M. (2005). 2.45 GHz radiofrequency fields alter gene expression in cultured human cells. FEBS Lett. 579, 4829-4836.

Mitchell, T.M. (1997). Machine Learning. McGraw-Hill,

Singapore.

Moulder, J.E., Erdreich, L.S., Malyapa, R.S., Merritt, J., Pickard, W.F., and Vijayalaxmi. (1999). Cell phones and

cancer: what is the evidence for a connection? Radiat Res.

151, 513-531.

Muscat, J.E., Malkin, M.G., Thompson, S., Shore, RE., Stellman, S.D., McRee, D., Neugut, A.I., and Wynder, E.L. (2000).

Handheld cellular telephone use and risk of brain cancer. JAA44 284, 3001-3007.

Park, W.Y., Hwang, C.I., Im, C.N., Kang, M.J., Woo, J.H., Kim, J.H., Kim, Y.S., Kim, J.H., Kim, H., Kim, K.A., Yu, H.J., Lee, S.J., Lee, Y.S., and Seo, J.S. (2002). Identification of radiation-specific responses from gene expression profile. Oncogene21, 8521-8528.

Platt, J. (1998). Fast training of support vector machines using sequential minimal optimization. Advances in kernel

methods - support vector learning. MIT Press.

Salford, L.G., Brun, A.E., Eberhardt, J.L., Malmgren, L., and Persson, B.R. (2003). Nerve cell damage in mammalian

brain after exposure to microwaves from GSM mobile

phones. Environ Heaith Perspect. 111, 881-883.

Tan, T.N., Stenbach, M., and Kumar, V. (2005). Introduction

to Data Mining, Addison Wesley.

Vapnik, V.N. (1998). Statistical Learning Theory. Wiley, New

York, NY.

Witten, I.J. and Frank, E. (2005). Data mining: practical machine learning tools with java implementations. 2nd ed., Morgan Kaufmann, San Francisco, CA.

Zook, B.C. and Simmens, S.J. (2006). The effects of pulsed

860 MHz radiofrequency radiation on the promotion of neurogenic tumors in rats. Radiat Res. 165, 608-615.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 5-----------------------------------------------------
