<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="review-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inf</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inf</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GNI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Genomics &amp; Informatics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korea Genome Organization</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23105934</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">3480682</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2012.10.2.81</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Review</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Identifying Copy Number Variants under Selection in Geographically Structured Populations Based on <italic>F</italic>-statistics</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Song</surname>
            <given-names>Hae-Hiang</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Hu</surname>
            <given-names>Hae-Jin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Seok</surname>
            <given-names>In-Hae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>Yeun-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Division of Biostatistics, Department of Medical Lifescience, The Catholic University of Korea, College of Medicine, Seoul 137-040, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Microbiology, Integrated Research Center for Genome Polymorphism, The Catholic University of Korea, College of Medicine, Seoul 137-040, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Department of Statistics, Hankuk University of Foreign Studies, Yongin 449-791, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="FN1"><sup>*</sup>Corresponding author 1: Tel: +82-2-2258-7225, Fax: +82-2-596-8969, <email xlink:type="simple">hhsong@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <corresp id="FN2"><sup>**</sup>Corresponding author 2: Tel: +82-2-2258-7343, Fax: +82-2-596-4513, <email xlink:type="simple">yejun@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2012</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>81</fpage>
      <lpage>87</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>17</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2012</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2012 by The Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2012</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0">
          <license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Large-scale copy number variants (CNVs) in the human provide the raw material for delineating population differences, as natural selection may have affected at least some of the CNVs thus far discovered. Although the examination of relatively large numbers of specific ethnic groups has recently started in regard to inter-ethnic group differences in CNVs, identifying and understanding particular instances of natural selection have not been performed. The traditional <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> measure, obtained from differences in allele frequencies between populations, has been used to identify CNVs loci subject to geographically varying selection. Here, we review advances and the application of multinomial-Dirichlet likelihood methods of inference for identifying genome regions that have been subject to natural selection with the <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> estimates. The contents of presentation are not new; however, this review clarifies how the application of the methods to CNV data, which remains largely unexplored, is possible. A hierarchical Bayesian method, which is implemented via Markov Chain Monte Carlo, estimates locus-specific <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and can identify outlying CNVs loci with large values of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>. By applying this Bayesian method to the publicly available CNV data, we identified the CNV loci that show signals of natural selection, which may elucidate the genetic basis of human disease and diversity.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>Bayes theorem</kwd>
        <kwd>DNA copy number variations</kwd>
        <kwd>population structure</kwd>
        <kwd>selection</kwd>
        <kwd>Wright's <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub></kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>It has become known that human genomes differ more as a consequence of structural variation than of single-base-pair differences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. Structural genomic variants, mainly in the form of copy number variants (CNVs), have recently been rediscovered as contributors to evolution and as pathoetiologic elements for complex human diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. However, so far, there are not many CNV-based genome-wide association studies or population genetics studies compared with the single-nucleotide polymorphism (SNP)-based counterparts. One notable CNV-based population genetics study was done by Jakobsson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. They applied SNP, haplotype, and CNV information to reveal the structures of 29 world-wide populations. Even though their CNVs were not as effective as SNPs or haplotypes in discriminating those populations, the authors showed the potential to apply this information to human genetic studies. Other examples of CNV-based disease susceptibility studies are systemic autoimmunity diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>], psoriasis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>], and human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection and progression to acquired immune deficiency syndrome (AIDS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]. Disease could affect the patterns of CNV diversity via natural selection, and higher copy numbers of the immunoregulatory and inflammatory cytokine gene <italic>CCL3L1</italic>, for example, are associated with lower risks of HIV infection and the progression to AIDS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>]; furthermore, in a genome-wide study, the level of population differentiation at this locus was found to be extraordinary compared to that of other CNVs, suggesting that natural selection may have influenced <italic>CCL3L1</italic> copy number in humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>The traditional <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> measure is useful for identifying regions of the genome affected by natural selection. In a recently published review paper, Holsinger and Weir define Wright's <italic>F</italic>-statistics (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> in particular) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] and describe methods-of-moment estimates and how <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> estimates should be interpreted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. Although the authors also mention the maximum likelihood Bayesian estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, their description is very limited in identifying genomic regions under selection and do not present an application to the datasets. They simply compared locus-specific estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> with its genome-wide distribution, and therefore, probabilities are not attached to those with a higher <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>.</p>
      <p>Here, we outline the steps that constitute testing for outlier loci in population datasets by the maximum likelihood Bayesian method, using BayeScan computer software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] (Note that the terms of locus and CNV are used interchangeably in this paper). The logic for determining outlier loci is simple. If natural selection favors one allele over others at a particular locus in some populations, the <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> at that locus will be larger than at loci in which among-population differences are purely a result of genetic drift. Therefore, genome scans that compare single-locus estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> with the genome-wide background might identify regions of the genome that have been subjected to diversifying selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>].</p>
      <p>We will demonstrate <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> estimation by maximum likelihood Bayesian method with the publicly available high-resolution CNV dataset generated by Conrad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. We will also show that this method identifies several genomic regions showing signals of natural selection. Even though we focus mainly on the CNV data here, the detailed steps of analysis are analogous for other types of molecular marker data, such as microsatellites, SNPs, and amplified fragment-length polymorphisms.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Method-of-moment (or ANOVA) estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub></title>
      <sec>
        <title><italic>F</italic>-statistics</title>
        <p>Wright [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] introduced <italic>F</italic>-statistics (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub>) as a tool for describing the partitioning of genetic diversity within and among populations that are directly related to the rates of evolutionary processes, such as migration, mutation, and drift. Specifically, <italic>F</italic>-statistics can be defined in many different ways: in terms of variances of allele frequencies, correlations between random gametes, and probabilities that two gametes chosen have different alleles. Depending on the relativity to the subpopulation or to the total population, <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> are defined, where subscript IS refers to 'individuals within subpopulations,' ST to 'subpopulations within the total population,' and IT to 'individuals within the total population.'</p>
        <p>Following the work of Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], <italic>F</italic>-statistics are defined in terms of the variance components - that is, the total variation in the genetic data is broken down into three components: (a) between subpopulations within the total population (we sometimes say 'between populations'); (b) between individuals within subpopulations; and (c) between gametes within individuals. <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> are defined as the expectations under the model of a/(a + b + c), (a + b)/(a + b + c), and b/(b + c) and estimated by the corresponding sample values [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. Here, it is perhaps pertinent to mention that when Weir and Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] presented these definitions, they assumed a model consisting of an ancestral population from which subpopulations have descended in isolation under the same evolutionary processes. Thus, it is meaningful to have a single measure of population structure; that is, a global <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, which is an average over subpopulations. However, in identifying candidate loci under natural selection, evidence for locus-specific selection is of interest, and thus the estimators of locus-specific <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> will be described in the next section.</p>
        <p>Often, readers may be confused with several terms appearing in population genetics. Wright [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>] interprets <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> as a measure of the progress of the subpopulation towards the fixation of one allele of each locus in the absence of mutation and hence called a 'fixation index.' <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> is also interpreted as a measure of shared ancestry with the subpopulations, relative to that in the population, and is thus called the 'coancestry coefficient' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Therefore, if the value of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> is small, it means that the allele frequencies within each subpopulation are similar; if it is large, it means that the allele frequencies of subpopulations are different. On the other hand, <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> or <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub> is defined as the correlation between two gametes that form a zygote relative to the subpopulation or population, and thus, <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> (or <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub>) is called the 'inbreeding coefficient' [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Estimating <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> by ANOVA methods</title>
        <p>The estimators of <italic>F</italic>-statistics proposed by Weir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and Weir and Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] are based on an analysis of variance (ANOVA) of allele frequencies, equivalently called the method-of-moments estimates. The weighted ANOVA estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, <italic>F</italic><sub>IT</sub>, and <italic>F</italic><sub>IS</sub> may be expressed in terms of the mean sum of squares for gametes (<italic>MSG</italic>), individuals (<italic>MSI</italic>), and populations (we sometimes say 'between subpopulations') (<italic>MSP</italic>), where the mean squares are estimated by an ANOVA model. In estimating <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> specifically for our analysis of CNV data, we need to consider unbalanced samples (i.e., populations of unequal size). However, as the formulas are messy, we present here those for balanced samples. Formulas for unbalanced samples can be found in Rousset (in Appendix A) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref>].</p>
        <p>The definition of <italic>F</italic>-statistics used here is</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e001"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>where <italic>Q</italic> values are probabilities of identity in state: <italic>Q<sub>1</sub></italic> among the genes (gametes) within individuals, <italic>Q<sub>2</sub></italic> among genes in different individuals within populations, and <italic>Q<sub>3</sub></italic> among the populations. The estimates <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i002.jpg"/></inline-formula> are expressed in terms of observed frequencies of identical pairs of genes in the sample, with the following relationships:</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e002"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>and</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e003"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>where <italic>n</italic> is the sample size of each population. Then, the single locus estimator <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i003.jpg"/></inline-formula> is given by</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(1)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e004"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>which is found in Weir (1997: 178) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>]. <italic>n<sub>c</sub></italic> will be defined below. If one needs to obtain the multilocus estimator of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i003.jpg"/></inline-formula>, it is usual to compute the estimator as a sum of locus-specific numerators over a sum of locus-specific denominators (see Weir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and Weir and Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]). This is the case that map information for SNPs is obtained for each gene, and a weighted-average <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> from all SNPs is estimated for each gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. For a set of <italic>I</italic> loci, the multilocus ANOVA estimators are</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(2)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e005"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>for <italic>n<sub>c</sub></italic> = (<italic>S</italic><sub>1</sub>-<italic>S</italic><sub>2</sub>/<italic>S</italic><sub>1</sub>)/(<italic>n</italic>-1), where <italic>S<sub>1</sub></italic> is the total sample size and <italic>S</italic><sub>2</sub> is the sum of squared sample sizes of populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>]. For convenience, we denote the estimator <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i003.jpg"/></inline-formula> by <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>.</p>
        <p>Rousset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>] explained that the multilocus estimators of Weir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and Weir and Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>] differ slightly, and these two also differ slightly from that proposed by Rousset [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">21</xref>], which assigns more weight to larger samples. In this paper, the GENEPOP software (version 3.4) (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wbiomed.curtin.edu.au/genepop/">http://wbiomed.curtin.edu.au/genepop/</ext-link>) of Rousset was used for the calculation of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>. In order to distinguish from those of the method-of-moments estimates of Weir [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>] and Weir and Cockerham [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], we will call the estimates of GENEPOP ANOVA estimates.</p>
        <p>The estimated values of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> can be negative when levels of differentiation are close to zero and/or sample sizes are small, indicating no population differentiation at these loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. One can assign a value of zero to negative <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> estimates.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Identifying CNVs under Selection Using a Bayesian Method</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Identifying selection</title>
        <p>Identifying candidate CNVs under natural selection using locus-specific estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> is of great interest, in view of our increased knowledge of the relationships among human populations from genome-wide patterns of variation. The logic for identifying selection is straightforward. The pattern of genetic differentiation at a neutral locus is completely determined by the demographic history, migration rates among the populations, and the mutation rates at the loci. It is reasonable to assume that all autosomal loci have experienced the same demographic history and migration rates among the populations, and the observed population structure can be largely explained by random drift at neutral loci. However, as the individuals from different populations often vary genetically at a few key sites in their genome, loci showing unusually large amounts of differentiation may indicate regions of the genome that have been subject to positive selection, whereas loci showing unusually small amounts of differentiation may indicate regions of the genome that have been subject to stabilizing (balancing) selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. Thus, the outlier method makes it possible to detect divergences in some loci of the genome due to selection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Bayesian method</title>
        <p>Balding and Nichols have proposed the use of population- and locus-specific estimates in the context of a migration-drift equilibrium model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>]. They modeled allele frequencies of biallelic markers using a beta distribution with expectation <italic>p</italic> and variance <italic>p</italic>(1-p)/(1+&#x3B8;) so that <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> = 1/(1+&#x3B8;). Then, they used a likelihood-based approach to estimate population- and locus-specific <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>.</p>
        <p>This formulation was extended later to consider multiallelic loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>]. Falush et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>] considered the nonequilibrium fission model that subpopulations evolve in isolation after splitting from an ancestral population. We will not distinguish the migration-drift equilibrium model and nonequilibrium fission model, since both lead to the same multinomial-Dirichlet distribution (or beta-binomial for biallelic loci) for the subpopulation allele frequencies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. The main difference between the two models resides in the interpretation given to <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>: in the case of the migration-drift equilibrium model, <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> measures how divergent each subpopulation is from the total population, while in the case of the fission model, it measures the degree of genetic differentiation between each descendant population and the ancestral population.</p>
        <p>We consider a collection of <italic>J</italic> subpopulations and a set of <italic>I</italic> loci. Let <italic>K<sub>i</sub></italic>&gt; be the number of alleles at the <italic>i</italic> th locus. The extent of differentiation between subpopulation <italic>j</italic> and the ancestral population at locus <italic>i</italic> is measured by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula>. Let <bold>p</bold><italic><sub>i</sub></italic> = { <italic>p<sub>ik</sub></italic> } denote the allele frequencies of the ancestral population at locus <italic>i</italic>, where <italic>p<sub>ik</sub></italic> is the frequency of the allele <italic>k</italic> at locus <italic>i</italic>(<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i005.jpg"/></inline-formula> = 1). We use <bold>p</bold> = { <bold>p</bold><italic><sub>i</sub></italic> } to denote the entire set of allele frequencies of the ancestral population and <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i006.jpg"/></inline-formula> to denote the current allele frequencies at locus <italic>i</italic> for subpopulation <italic>j</italic>. Under the model and the definitions above, the allele frequencies at locus <italic>i</italic> in subpopulation <italic>j</italic> follow a Dirichlet distribution with parameters &#x3B8;<sub>j</sub><bold>p</bold><sub>i</sub>, a Bayesian prior distribution,</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(3)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e006"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>where &#x3B8;<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> = 1/<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula>-1. The extent of differentiation at locus <italic>i</italic> between subpopulation <italic>j</italic> and the ancestral population is measured by <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> and is the result of its demographic history. The full prior distribution across loci and populations is given by</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(4)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e007"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>We need a hierarchical model for locus- and population-specific effects to identify candidate loci under natural selection. It is no doubt that population- and locus-specific estimates of <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> by the moments (or ANOVA) methods are likely to be inaccurate, especially for loci with a small number of different alleles. As an alternative, Beaumont and Balding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>] proposed a familiar logistic regression model to decompose population- and locus-specific <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> coefficients (bounded between 0 and 1) into a population-specific component, &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic>, shared by all loci and a locus-specific component, &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>, shared by all populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]:</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(5)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e008"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>The locus-specific effects express mutation and some forms of selection, and population-specific effects express migration rates, population sizes, and population-specific mating patterns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. The advantage of this formulation is that instead of estimating locus- and population-specific <italic>I</italic>&#xB7;<italic>J</italic>
<inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> coefficients (as in the method of moments or ANOVA), we only have to estimate <italic>I</italic> the parameters &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> and the <italic>J</italic> parameters &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic>. With the estimates of &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> and &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic>, <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> (and equivalently &#x3B8;<italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> = exp(-(&#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> + &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic>)) can be estimated.</p>
        <p>Above all, the estimate of &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is our objective to detect outlier loci as selection candidates. Departure from neutrality at a given locus is assumed when &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is significantly different from 0 at that locus. A positive value of &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> suggests diversifying selection, whereas negative values suggest balancing selection. The posterior probability that a locus is subject to selection, <italic>P</italic>(&#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &#x2260; 0), is estimated directly from the Markov Chain Monte Carlo method (MCMC) (see below).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Likelihood for allele counts</title>
        <p>The data of codominant markers consist of allele counts obtained from samples of size <italic>n</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic>. We use &#x3B1;<italic><sub>ijk</sub></italic> to denote the number of alleles <italic>k</italic> observed at locus <italic>i</italic> in the sample from subpopulation <italic>j</italic>. Thus, <italic>n</italic><italic><sub>ij</sub></italic> = &#x3A3;<italic><sub>k</sub></italic>&#x3B1;<italic><sub>ijk</sub></italic>. The full dataset can be presented as a matrix <bold>N</bold> = { <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold> }, where <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold> = { &#x3B1;<italic><sub>ij1</sub></italic>, &#x3B1;<italic><sub>ij2</sub></italic>, ..., &#x3B1;<italic><sub>ijK<sub>i</sub></sub></italic> } is the allele count at locus <italic>i</italic> for subpopulation <italic>j</italic>. The observed allele frequencies, <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold>, can be considered as sampled from the true alleles frequencies <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i007.jpg"/></inline-formula> and therefore can be described by the multinomial distribution:</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(6)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e009"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>We adopt the multinomial-Dirichlet distribution as a marginal distribution of <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold>, the allele frequency counts at a locus within a subpopulation, and the reasons of its adoption are explained in Foll and Gaggiotti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]:</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e010"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>The joint likelihood for allele counts is obtained by multiplying across all loci and populations:</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(7)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e011"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>Since the allele frequencies in the ancestral population <bold>p</bold><italic><sub>i</sub></italic> = { <italic>p<sub>ik</sub></italic> } are unknown, they are estimated by introducing a noninformative Dirichlet prior, <bold>p</bold><sub>i</sub> ~ Dir (1, &#x2026; , 1), into the Bayesian model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p>
        <p>The full Bayesian model is given by</p>
        <p>
          <disp-formula>
            <label>(8)</label>
            <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-e012"/>
          </disp-formula>
        </p>
        <p>Following Beaumont and Balding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>], the Gaussian prior distributions are used for the population effects &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> and for the locus effects &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic>. Their means and variances are chosen to improve convergence and for each <inline-formula><inline-graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i004.jpg"/></inline-formula> to have non-negligible density over almost the whole interval from 0 to 1.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Identifying CNVs subject to selection</title>
        <p>As described above, the effect of selection is parameterized by &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> in the logistic regression. Thus, two models in the logistic, one that includes both effects of &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> (i.e., &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &#x2260; 0) and &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> (selection model, M2) and another one that does not include the effect of selection (i.e., &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> = 0) and only includes the effect of &#x3B2;<italic><sub>j</sub></italic> (neutral model, M1), are considered.</p>
        <p>We can decide in a Bayesian framework whether or not there is selection at all. This is done by estimating the posterior probabilities for two models for each locus in the logistic regression: neutral (M1) and selection (model 2, M2), on the basis of a dataset <bold>N</bold> = { <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold> }. We use a reversible jump MCMC algorithm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>] to estimate the posterior probability of each one of these models, and this is done separately for each locus <italic>i</italic>. We can then have posterior probability that a locus is subject to selection - that is, <italic>P</italic>(&#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> &#x2260;0). This probability is estimated directly from the output of the MCMC by simply counting the number of times &#x3B1;<italic><sub>i</sub></italic> is included in the model (see Foll and Gaggiotti [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] for a more detailed explanation).</p>
        <p>In BayeScan, selection decision (model choice decision), with a specific goal of detecting outlier loci in mind, is actually performed by using posterior odds (PO). For this, we first need to describe 'Bayes factors.' For the two models of neutral (M1) and selection (M2), the Bayes factor (BF) for model M2 is given by BF = <italic>P</italic>(<bold>N</bold> | M2)/<italic>P</italic>(<bold>N</bold> | M1), where <bold>N</bold> = { <bold>a<sub>ij</sub></bold> } is a dataset and <italic>P</italic> indicates probability. This BF provides a degree of evidence in favor of one model versus another. In the context of multiple testing - that is, testing a large number of loci simultaneously - we also need to incorporate our skepticism about the chance that each locus is under selection. This is done by setting the prior odds for the neutral model <italic>P</italic>(M1)/<italic>P</italic>(M2). We make selection decisions by using PO, which is defined as PO = <italic>P</italic>(M2|<bold>N</bold>)/<italic>P</italic>(M1|<bold>N</bold>) = BF &#xD7; <italic>P</italic>(M2)/<italic>P</italic>(M1). PO are simply the ratio of posterior probabilities and indicate how much more likely the model with selection (M2) is compared to the neutral model (M1) (GENEPOP software). PO of 0.5-1.0, 1.0-1.5, 1.5-2.0, and 2-&#x221E; are, respectively, considered as substantial, strong, very strong, and decisive evidence for selection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>].</p>
        <p>A big advantage of posterior probabilities is that they directly allow the control of the false discovery rate (FDR), where FDR is defined as the expected proportion of false positives among outlier loci. Controlling for FDR has a much greater power than controlling for family-wise error rates using Bonferroni correction, for example [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In BayeScan, by first setting a target FDR, the PO threshold achieving this FDR is determined, and outliers equal to or above this PO threshold are listed in the output of R that is provided along with BayeScan.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Empirical Distribution of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> Based on CNV</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Study populations</title>
        <p>We obtained the high-resolution CNV data by Conrad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] from the Database of Genomic Variants (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://projects.tcag.ca/variation/">http://projects.tcag.ca/variation/</ext-link>). The dataset consists of 90 Han Chinese (CHB) and Japanese (JPT), 180 Caucasians of European descent (CEU), and 180 Yoruba (YRI) samples. Among the 450 individuals, we removed 19 individuals with more than 400 missing CNV genotypes. Each CNV was analyzed as biallelic dominant data, classified as neutral versus non-neutral (losses or gains).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Empirical distribution of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub></title>
        <p>To assess population differentiation with an allele frequency spectrum of CNVs, the locus-specific estimates by ANOVA method and by hierarchical Bayesian method were obtained from all autosomes. The estimated values by the ANOVA method (moments estimates) can be negative when levels of differentiation are close to 0 and/or sample sizes are small, indicating no population differentiation at these loci [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>]. In the hierarchical Bayesian method, the locus-specific estimate values are all positive, since they are generated by posterior distributions, which is an important benefit of a Bayesian method.</p>
        <p>With the CNV data of this study, the summary statistics of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> was 0.0853 &#xB1; 0.1195 (median, 0.0360; range, -0.0071 to 0.8994) for the ANOVA method and 0.2459 &#xB1; 0.0115 (median, 0.2462; range, 0.2193 to 0.6166) for the Bayesian method. The empirical distributions of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> are found in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>. As can be seen from the Figure, low <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> values are prevalent, and a large variability persisted in the ANOVA method, while <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> distribution was sharply focused in the Bayesian method. The comparison of empirical distributions of the ANOVA and Bayesian methods demonstrates that Bayesian estimates perform better than ANOVA in identifying CNVs affected by natural selection.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Bayesian outlier detections</title>
        <p>We searched the genome regions that show signals of natural selection by the Bayesian likelihood method implemented via reversible jump MCMC in BayeScan software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. For each CNV, BayeScan directly estimates the probability that a CNV is under positive selection, from which the PO are computed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The posterior odds indicate how much more likely the model with selection is compared to the neutral model, and posterior odds of 5.0 was chosen as a threshold in the detection of CNVs under positive selection. This directly allows us to control the FDR, the expected proportion of false positives among outlier CNVs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">29</xref>]. In our analysis, we chose FDR to be 0.05. In the BayeScan application, first following 10 pilot runs of 5,000 iterations and an additional burn-in of 50,000 iterations, we used 50,000 iterations (sample size of 5,000 and a thinning interval of 10).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Outliers detected by BayeScan</title>
        <p>BayeScan identified the three outlier CNVs with Conrad et al.'s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>] CNV data (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). The most decisive outlier is CNVR2664.1 (chromosome 5), in which most CEU (90%) and all CHB + JPT populations are outlying gain or loss status. The next decisive outlier is CNVR371.1 (chr. 1), in which only the YRI population has non-neutral CNVs.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>In general, the observed population structure observed by hierarchical clustering, multidimensional scaling (MDS) plots, and tree plots can be largely explained by random drift at neutral CNVs. However, as individuals from different populations often vary genetically at a few key sites in their genome, only the outlier method makes it possible to detect accelerated divergence in some CNV regions of the genome due to local selection. This local selection is detected relative to the majority of CNVs, in which among-population differences are purely a result of genetic drift.</p>
      <p>Successful outlier detection depends on reliable and obtainable estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and also on sampling variances of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>. Very large variances that are associated with single locus moment estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> preclude the use of these estimates to detect selection in spite of the fact that sampling variances will decrease with the number of alleles at a locus and with the numbers of populations sampled. In this respect, the availability of locus- and population-specific Bayesian estimates of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> provides a set of tools for identifying genomic regions or populations with unusual evolutionary histories. The most important benefits of Bayesian estimates and its selection method are that the Bayesian methods allow probability statements to be made about <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and can be extended to explore the relationship with demographic or environmental covariates in the model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>]. Furthermore, likelihood-based Bayesian methods have the flexibility to accommodate missing data. However, implementations of Bayesian methods may be computationally demanding.</p>
      <p>Selection provides information about the adaptation to a wide range of habitats and climates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], and thus, interpreting the story of human adaptation is an interesting research area for the studies of evolution and disease processes in the future. Thus, more studies of outlier detection need to be replicated with large population-based data.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This study was supported by a grant from the Korea Healthcare Technology R&amp;D Project (A092258), Ministry of Health and Welfare, Republic of Korea.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sebat</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lakshmi</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Troge</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Young</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lundin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Large-scale copy number polymorphism in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>305</volume>
          <fpage>525</fpage>
          <lpage>528</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15273396</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tuzun</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sharp</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bailey</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaul</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morrison</surname>
              <given-names>VA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pertz</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fine-scale structural variation of the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>727</fpage>
          <lpage>732</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15895083</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Redon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitch</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feuk</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perry</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Global variation in copy number in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>444</volume>
          <fpage>444</fpage>
          <lpage>454</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17122850</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Conrad</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinto</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Redon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feuk</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gokcumen</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Origins and functional impact of copy number variation in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>464</volume>
          <fpage>704</fpage>
          <lpage>712</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19812545</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lupski</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genomic disorders: structural features of the genome can lead to DNA rearrangements and human disease traits</article-title>
          <source>Trends Genet</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>417</fpage>
          <lpage>422</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9820031</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stankiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lupski</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genome architecture, rearrangements and genomic disorders</article-title>
          <source>Trends Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>74</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11818139</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jakobsson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scholz</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scheet</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibbs</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>VanLiere</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fung</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genotype, haplotype and copy-number variation in worldwide human populations</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>451</volume>
          <fpage>998</fpage>
          <lpage>1003</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18288195</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fanciulli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norsworthy</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petretto</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dong</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harper</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamesh</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>FCGR3B</italic> copy number variation is associated with susceptibility to systemic, but not organ-specific, autoimmunity</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>721</fpage>
          <lpage>723</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17529978</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>YL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savelli</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagaraja</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gene copy-number variation and associated polymorphisms of complement component C4 in human systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE): low copy number is a risk factor for and high copy number is a protective factor against SLE susceptibility in European Americans</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>1037</fpage>
          <lpage>1054</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17503323</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hollox</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huffmeier</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zeeuwen</surname>
              <given-names>PL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Palla</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lascorz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodijk-Olthuis</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psoriasis is associated with increased beta-defensin genomic copy number</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18059266</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gonzalez</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kulkarni</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bolivar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mangano</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanchez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Catano</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The influence of CCL3L1 gene-containing segmental duplications on HIV-1/AIDS susceptibility</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>307</volume>
          <fpage>1434</fpage>
          <lpage>1440</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15637236</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The genetical structure of populations</article-title>
          <source>Ann Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1949</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>323</fpage>
          <lpage>354</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Holsinger</surname>
              <given-names>KE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weir</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics in geographically structured populations: defining, estimating and interpreting F(ST)</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Genet</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>639</fpage>
          <lpage>650</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19687804</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foll</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>BayeScan v2.0 User Manual</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <publisher-name>BayeScan</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B15">
        <label>15</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akey</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jin</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shriver</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interrogating a high-density SNP map for signatures of natural selection</article-title>
          <source>Genome Res</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1805</fpage>
          <lpage>1814</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12466284</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B16">
        <label>16</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cockerham</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analyses of gene frequencies</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <fpage>679</fpage>
          <lpage>700</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17248636</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B17">
        <label>17</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weir</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Genetic Data Analysis II: Methods for Discrete Population Genetic Data</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <publisher-loc>Sunderland</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Sinauer Associates</publisher-name>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B18">
        <label>18</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weir</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cockerham</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structure</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>1358</fpage>
          <lpage>1370</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B19">
        <label>19</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balding</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Likelihood-based inference for genetic correlation coefficients</article-title>
          <source>Theor Popul Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <fpage>221</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12689793</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B20">
        <label>20</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rousset</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Balding</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bishop</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cannings</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inferences from spatial population genetics</article-title>
          <source>Handbook of Statistical Genetics</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>269</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B21">
        <label>21</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rousset</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>genepop'007: a complete re-implementation of the genepop software for Windows and Linux</article-title>
          <source>Mol Ecol Resour</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21585727</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B22">
        <label>22</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beaumont</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balding</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identifying adaptive genetic divergence among populations from genome scans</article-title>
          <source>Mol Ecol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>969</fpage>
          <lpage>980</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15012769</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B23">
        <label>23</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vitalis</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dawson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boursot</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interpretation of variation across marker loci as evidence of selection</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>158</volume>
          <fpage>1811</fpage>
          <lpage>1823</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11514464</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B24">
        <label>24</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beaumont</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nichols</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluating loci for use in the genetic analysis of population structure</article-title>
          <source>Proc R Soc Lond Series B Biol Sci</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>263</volume>
          <fpage>1619</fpage>
          <lpage>1626</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B25">
        <label>25</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Falush</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inference of population structure using multilocus genotype data: linked loci and correlated allele frequencies</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>164</volume>
          <fpage>1567</fpage>
          <lpage>1587</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12930761</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B26">
        <label>26</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foll</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaggiotti</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Identifying the environmental factors that determine the genetic structure of populations</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>174</volume>
          <fpage>875</fpage>
          <lpage>891</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16951078</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B27">
        <label>27</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Foll</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaggiotti</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A genome-scan method to identify selected loci appropriate for both dominant and codominant markers: a Bayesian perspective</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>180</volume>
          <fpage>977</fpage>
          <lpage>993</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18780740</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B28">
        <label>28</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Green</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reversible jump Markov chain Monte Carlo computation and Bayesian model determination</article-title>
          <source>Biometrika</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>711</fpage>
          <lpage>732</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B29">
        <label>29</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Benjamini</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hochberg</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title>
          <source>J R Stat Soc Series B Methodol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>300</lpage>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B30">
        <label>30</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Voight</surname>
              <given-names>BF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kudaravalli</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wen</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pritchard</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A map of recent positive selection in the human genome</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>e72</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16494531</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Empirical distributions of copy number variants (CNV) data with the three population groups. CNV data are from Conrad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>].</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Spacial scans for identification of <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> outlier copy number variants (CNVs) potentially subject to positive selection by BayeScan. CNV data are from Conrad et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>]. PO, posterior odds.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-g002"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Identified outlier CNVs potentially subject to positive selection by BayeScan</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-10-81-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>CNV, copy number variants; CEU, Caucasians of European descent; CHB, Han Chinese; JPT, Japanese; YRI, Yoruba.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>