G&I

Genomics & Informatics

eISSN 2234-0742

Genomics & Informatics Genomics Inform Vol. 15, 2017;15(3):81 No. 3, 2017

https://doi.org/10.5808/GI.2017.15.3.81

EDITORIAL

Editor’s Introduction to This Issue (G&I 15:3, 2017)

Yeun-Jun Chung*

Precision Medicine Research Center, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul 06591, Korea

In this issue, Drs. Sun Ho Lee and Wung Joo Song report copy number variations in 42 Korean patients with unexplained developmental disorders by chromosomal microarray (no chromosomal alteration was detected by conventional karyotyping or fluorescent in situ hybridi- zation). They found clinically relevant copy number varia- tions in over 60% of tested patients, which suggests the superior diagnostic performance of chromosomal micro- array analysis. Dr. Sun-Young Kong’s group observed chro- mothripsis events in several myeloma cell lines and bone marrow samples of multiple myeloma patients. They found that the number of chromothripsis-like events increased
 after drug treatment and that chromothripsis-like events were more frequent in the drug-resistant group. Dr. Heui-Soo Kim’s group explored the evolutionary conser- vation of miR-21-3p in various species and the expression patterns of target genes in olive flounder. In the application note section, Dr. Buhm Han’s group report an interesting tool, called ‘MergeReference.’ This tool supports the imputation of human leukocyte antigen genes using inter- genic single nucleotide polymorphism markers.

For further details, please visit the G&I homepage

(https://www.genominfo.org/).

* Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-2258-7343, Fax: +82-2-537-0572, E-mail: yejun@catholic.ac.kr

Copyright © 2017 by the Korea Genome Organization

CC It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/).

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
