A R T IC L E

Genomics & Informatics                                         ttp://dx.doi.org/10.5808/GI.2012.10.1.33

Vol. 10(1) 33-39, March 2012                                                       pISSN 1598-866X eISSN 2234-0742

CaGe: A Web-Based Cancer Gene Annotation System for Cancer Genomics

Young-Kyu Park 1,2 , Tae-Wook Kang 1 , Su-Jin Baek 1,3 , Kwon-Il Kim 2 , Seon-Young Kim 1,3 , Doheon Lee 2 * and Yong Sung Kim 1,3 **

1 Medical Genomics Research Center, KRIBB, Daejeon

2 3

of Functional Genomics, University of Science and Technology, Daejeon 305-806, Korea

Abstract

High-throughput genomic technologies (HGTs), including next-generation DNA sequencing (NGS), microarray, and serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE), have become effective experimental tools for cancer genomics to identify cancer-associated somatic genomic alterations and genes. The main hurdle in cancer genomics is to identify the real causative mutations or genes out of many candidates from an HGT-based cancer genomic analysis. One useful approach is to refer to known can- cer genes and associated information. The list of known cancer genes can be used to determine candidates of cancer driver mutations, while cancer gene-related in- formation, including gene expression, protein-protein in- teraction, and pathways, can be useful for scoring novel candidates. Some cancer gene or mutation databases exist for this purpose, but few specialized tools exist for an automated analysis of a long gene list from an HGT-based cancer genomic analysis. This report pres- ents a new web-accessible bioinformatic tool, called CaGe, a cancer genome annotation system for the as- sessment of candidates of cancer genes from HGT- based cancer genomics. The tool provides users with information on cancer-related genes, mutations, path- ways, and associated annotations through annotation and browsing functions. With this tool, researchers can classify their candidate genes from cancer genome studies into either previously reported or novel catego- ries of cancer genes and gain insight into underlying carcinogenic mechanisms through a pathway analysis. We show the usefulness of CaGe by assessing its per-

*Corresponding author1: E-mail: dhlee@biosoft.kaist.ac.kr Tel +82-42-350-4316, Fax +82-42-350-8680

**Corresponding author2: E-mail: yongsung@kribb.re.kr Tel +82-42-879-8110, Fax +82-42-879-8119

Received 26 January 2012, Revised 10 February 2012, Accepted 16 February 2012

formance in annotating somatic mutations from a pub- lished small cell lung cancer study.

Keywords: annotation, cancer gene, high-throughput ge- nomic technology, mutation, next-generation sequenc- ing, pathway

Availability: CaGe is freely available at http://mgrc.kribb. re.kr/cage.

Introduction

High-throughput genomic technologies (HGTs), including next-generation DNA sequencing (NGS), microarray, and serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE), have become effective tools for cancer genomics through various applications. Especially, the applications of NGS include whole-genome, exome, and transcriptome approaches for searching for a wide range of cancer-specific geno- mic alterations, such as point mutations, insertions, and deletions; copy number changes; and rearrangements, leading to the development of cancer [1].

One of the hurdles in HGT-based cancer genomics is to identify causative mutations or genes out of many candidates from the analysis. A useful approach is to refer to known cancer genes and associated information [2]. The list of known cancer genes can be used to de- termine candidates of cancer driver mutations, while cancer gene-related information, such as gene expres- sion, protein-protein interaction, and pathway informa- tion, can be useful for scoring novel candidates. Some useful cancer genomic databases for this pur- pose exist, including Cancer Gene Census (CGC) [3] and Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer (COSMIC) [4], which have been constructed and managed by the Cancer Genome Project of the Welcome Trust Sanger Institute; and Cancer Gene Index (CGI, http://ncicb.nci. nih.gov/NCICB/projects/cgdcp), The Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA, http://cancergenome.nih.gov), and Cancer Ge- nome Anatomy Project (CGAP, http://cgap.nci.nih.gov), which are maintained by the National Cancer Institute of the U. S. National Institute of Health and National Hu- man Genome Research Institute. Among them, COSMIC and CGC are the two most commonly used resources among researchers when checking reported cancer driv- er mutations. The COSMIC database stores information on somatic mutations and associated information ex- tracted from the scientific literature, while the CGC da-

305-806, Korea, Department of Bio and Brain Engi-

neering, KAIST, Daejeon 305-701, Korea, Department

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
34 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 10(1) 33-39, March 2012

tabase is a catalog of cancer genes with manually screened somatic mutations extracted from the lite- rature. These cancer genes are annotated with infor- mation concerning chromosomal location, tumor types in which mutations are found, classes of mutations that contribute to oncogenesis, and other genetic properties. Also, CGI is known to be created through an automated linguistic text analysis of millions of MEDLINE abstracts, with manual validation and annotation of the extracted data by expert curators. It is a high-quality data re- source consisting of genes that have been experi- mentally associated with human cancer diseases and/or pharmacological compounds, the evidence of these as- sociations, and relevant annotations on the data. Thus, it can also be a valuable resource to annotate mutation data from cancer genomics studies.

Currently, few specialized tools exist for an automated analysis of a long gene list from HGT-based cancer genomics. While previously described cancer genomic information databases can be useful, they are not effec- tive in processing results from NGS-based cancer ge- nomic studies. Meanwhile, there are many functional an- notation systems to analyze gene lists derived from high-throughput microarray experiments, including DAVID [5], GoMiner [6], GOstat [7], Onto-express [8], and gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) [9]. DAVID is one of the most popular general purpose functional annotation

systems. It provides various effective analysis tools and is also applicable in the analysis of gene lists from can- cer genomics research. However, DAVID is not opti- mized for processing results from HGT-based cancer genomics data, especially for NGS-based cancer ge- nomics downstream data; therefore, a more specialized cancer gene annotation system is needed.

Here, we introduce a web-accessible cancer genome annotation system, named CaGe, to provide users with information on cancer genes, mutations, pathways, and associated annotations, based on several cancer gene databases composed of reported cancer-causing genes and associated cancer pathways. For a given gene list, CaGe searches cancer gene databases with converted standard gene symbols, analyzes the biological path- ways, and provides various cancer gene-related annota- tions through intuitive web user interfaces. It also serves additional functions, including processing various input types and formats, managing jobs for user submitted tasks, and browsing for cancer genes and pathways with various useful hyperlinks between the annotations and the external public annotation databases. We hope CaGe will be useful in identifying cancer-causing muta- tions and genes in HGT-based cancer genomics.

Fig. 1. Construction and main service flows of CaGe. SIFT, Sorting Into- lerant From Tolerant; NGS, next-generation DNA se- quencing; HGNC, HUGO Gene Nomenclature Com- mittee; CGC, Cancer Gene Census; CGI, Cancer Gene Index.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 2-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Methods

The goal of this study was to provide researchers with a tool for classifying their candidate genes from HGT- based cancer genome studies into previously reported or novel categories of cancer genes, while providing in- sight into underlying carcinogenic mechanisms through a pathway analysis. To implement the cancer gene an- notation function of CaGe, we constructed reported cancer gene and cancer annotation databases from public cancer genomic databases and cancer pathway- gene databases by pathway analysis with reported can- cer gene sets and canonical pathways. We also con- structed a gene ID database to allow various input for- mats for the input of gene lists and a gene functional annotation database to provide users with functional clues for the annotated candidate genes. Then, we de- veloped a core retrieval program and web interfaces for the main functions, which include cancer gene annota- tion, cancer pathway annotation, cancer gene browsing, and cancer pathway browsing. The workflow for the da- tabase construction and data processing in CaGe is summarized in Fig. 1, and the cancer gene annotation page of the CaGe web interface is shown in Fig. 2.

Cancer Gene Annotator   35

Cancer gene and annotation data

To construct the reported cancer gene database, we used gene sets from the CGC database (released on Dec, 2010) and CGI database (downloaded on Feb, 2011). The cancer pathways for the cancer pathway gene database construction were assigned based on statistical significance from one-tailed Fisher ’ s exact test for overlapping genes between reported cancer gene sets and canonical pathways from public pathway data- bases, including KEGG (Release 57.0), BioCarta, and Reactome (downloaded on Feb, 2011).

We also created a gene ID database to convert vari- ous input identifiers into standard gene symbols with HUGO Gene Nomenclature Committee (HGNC) (down- loaded on Feb, 2011) data for the standard gene sym- bols and with Entrez Gene (downloaded on Feb, 2011) and UniProt (Release 2011_03) data for the gene IDs, protein IDs, and functional annotations.

Input types

Available input types include a list of gene symbols, Entrez gene IDs, or UniProt accessions and output files

Fig. 2. Cancer gene annota- tion page of CaGe web inter- face.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 3-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
36 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 10(1) 33-39, March 2012

from prediction tools, such as Sorting Intolerant From Tolerant (SIFT) [10] and PolyPhen [11], which evaluate functional effects of mutations on proteins. CaGe parses the output of those tools to extract the list of genes that have somatic mutations evaluated as functionally dam- aging, classify them into previously reported and novel candidate cancer genes, and conduct pathway analyses to give insights into underlying carcinogenic mecha- nisms. Thus, CaGe offers straightforward data process-
 ing from HGT-based data without additional data con- version.

Cancer gene and pathway annotation workflow After acquiring user input, CaGe converts various input gene IDs into standard gene symbols, finds known can- cer genes and pathways, links various cancer-related annotations to matched genes, and outputs them in the

Fig. 3. Cancer gene annotation results page of CaGe web inter- face.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 4-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
form of tables or text files through the web interface (Fig. 3). Another function of CaGe is to identify over-rep- resented cancer-related or other biological pathways from the input gene list by performing one-tailed Fisher ’ s exact test.

When processing more than one annotation job, users can manage their annotation tasks through the CaGe in- terface, and access to their results is maintained by the internal job database of CaGe until the jobs are deleted by the user or by a scheduled cleaning process. The IP addresses of client computers are used for secured job management without a logon process. Completed anno- tation jobs are listed on the job table, and the annotated results can be shown selectively by the user on the an- notation result page or can be downloaded as tab-de- limited text files for further analyses. The annotation on

Cancer Gene Annotator   37

the results page has many useful links to gene and can- cer-related information in the CaGe database or external public databases. In addition to the cancer gene and pathway annotation function, CaGe provides a function to browse cancer genes and pathways so that users can search cancer-related annotations without an input list. The search flows of cancer genes and pathways are connected to each other by crosslinks in the cancer gene information page or pathway information page.

Results and Discussion

Database and web interface

Based on the reported cancer-related gene sets from CGC and CGI, a cancer gene database and a cancer

Table 1. Cancer gene sets and cancer pathway gene sets in the CaGe database

No.            Cancer and pathway gene set             Gene set code            No. of genes           No. of significant

pathways   a

1          Cancer Gene Census                            CGC                     436                   n/a 2          Cancer Gene Index                              CGI                    7,181                   n/a 3          CGC-based Pathway Genes                    CGC_PATH                 5,790                   143 4          CGI-based Pathway Genes                     CGI_PATH                 6,744                   176

n/a, not available.

a Pathways with p-values ＜ 0.05 from Fisher's exact test.

Table 2. Annotations for a cancer gene provided by CaGe

Name                                Description                                       Example

Basic cancer gene annotations

Gene set                 Source database for known cancer genes or cancer
 CGC/CGI/CGC_PATH/CGI_PATH

related genes

Gene symbol Standard gene symbol                                  ABL/ABL2/BRCA2 Tumor type Type of tumor as mutation source                        AML/Prostate/Breast/Ovarian Cell type                 Cell type where mutation occurs                         Somatic/Germline

Mutation type Type of reported mutation 　                           Missense/Translocation/Deletion Cancer syndrome Cancer syndrome                                      Familial blastoma

Additional functional annotations

Gene symbol (Gene ID) Gene symbol (Entrez gene ID)                           BHD (201163)

Full name Full description of gene                                 Folliculin, Birt-Hogg-Dube syndrome Alias                     Other gene symbols                                   BHD, DKFZp547A118, FLCL, FLJ45004,

FLJ99377, MGC17998

Position                  Chromosome band where the gene having the mutation

is located

Database links             Identifiers (IDs) with hyperlinks to the public gene and

protein annotation databases

17p11.2

HGNC: 27310; OMIM: 607273;

Ensembl: ENSG00000154803; HPRD: 06278; UniProt: BHD

Molecular Genetics         Type of inheritance                                    Recessive/Dominant Tissue type               Tissue type of tumor                                   E (epithelial), M (mesenchymal)

Related pathways          Pathways where the gene is assigned                     Purine metabolism (KEGG) by Cancer Gene

Census (CGC) gene set

-----------------------------------------------------Page 5-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
38 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 10(1) 33-39, March 2012

pathway gene database were constructed by the de- scribed methods. In total, 436 CGC-originated and 7181 CGI-originated cancer genes were prepared for the re- ported cancer gene annotation. Additionally, 5,790 CGC-based and 6,744 CGI-based cancer pathway genes were assigned for the annotation of unreported but potential candidate genes (Table 1). The gene ID database for gene symbol conversion, based on HGNC, and the functional annotation database, based on Entrez Gene and UniProt database flat files, were constructed. The types of annotations provided by CaGe are sum- marized in Table 2.

The main window of the CaGe web interface is shown in Fig. 2 for the cancer gene annotation process. Main menus, located in the upper part of the main win- dow, are linked to the four main functions and home page of the system: 1) home page, 2) cancer gene an- notation function, 3) cancer pathway annotation func- tion, 4) cancer gene browsing function, and 5) cancer pathway browsing function. Detailed usages for CaGe are described in the user ’ s guide at http://mgrc.kribb. re.kr/cage/include/cageUserGuide.pdf.

System information

CaGe was developed using PHP, R, and python lan- guages; MySQL for database management; and Apache for the web server and is operated on a Linux platform with 8-core Intel Xeon CPUs (2.33 GHz) and 24 GB of main memory.

Performance evaluation with small cell lung can- cer mutation data

To assess the capability of CaGe, we annotated genes from candidate mutations for a small cell lung cancer genome (SCLC) [12]. We had 59 genes with predicted functionally damaging mutations after applying 22,910 mutations to the PolyPhen and could annotate 22 pre- viously reported known cancer genes successfully by applying the PolyPhen output for CaGe. Known cancer genes included RB1 , which was mentioned as an SCLC-related gene in Pleasance ’ s work; DST and ETS2 , which were previously reported as SCLC-related genes but not mentioned in Pleasance ’ s work; and 3 more genes ( PDGFC , IL16 , and AGTR2 ), which are known as lung cancer-related genes (Supplementary Table 1). The other 16 genes are known to be related to other cancer types, suggesting that they might be important in the carcinogenesis of SCLC as well. From the pathway analysis, we identified 12 known cancer genes and 11 genes in cancer-related pathways (Supplementary Table 2). Those 11 genes might also be important in the carci-

nogenesis of SCLC. Thus, we conclude that CaGe can annotate cancer genes effectively and suggest that CaGe will be useful in the identification of cancer-caus- ing mutations and genes in HGT-based cancer geno- mics.

In this paper, we present a new cancer genomic tool, CaGe, for the assessment of candidate cancer genes having somatic mutations from HGT-based cancer genomics. CaGe provides users with information on cancer genes, mutations, pathways, and associated an- notations through cancer gene annotation, cancer path- way annotation, cancer gene browsing, and cancer pathway browsing functions. It has a capacity to proc- ess SIFT or PolyPhen output files as direct input for usual NGS-based cancer genomics flows. Researchers can classify their candidate genes from cancer genome studies into previously known or novel categories of cancer genes and gain insight into the underlying carci- nogenic mechanisms through a pathway analysis. We hope that CaGe will be useful for the identification of cancer-causing mutations and genes in HGT-based can- cer genomics.

Supplementary materials

Supplementary data including two tables can be found with this article online at http://www.genominfo.org/ html/UploadFile/article5_201203_SP.pdf.

Acknowledgments

This work was supported by grants from the KRIBB Research Initiative Program and from the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (MEST) (2010- 0012810) of the Republic of Korea. D.L. was supported by the Basic Research Laboratory grant (2009-0086964) of the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology through the National Research Foundation of Korea, and Korea Institute of Science and Technology Information (KISTI).

References

1. Meyerson M, Gabriel S, Getz G. Advances in under- standing cancer genomes through second-generation sequencing. Nat Rev Genet 2010;11:685-696.

2. Zang ZJ, Ong CK, Cutcutache I, Yu W, Zhang SL, Huang D, et al . Genetic and structural variation in the gastric cancer kinome revealed through targeted deep sequencing. Cancer Res 2011;71:29-39.

3. Futreal PA, Coin L, Marshall M, Down T, Hubbard T, Wooster R, et al . A census of human cancer genes. Nat Rev Cancer 2004;4:177-183.

4. Forbes SA, Bindal N, Bamford S, Cole C, Kok CY,

-----------------------------------------------------Page 6-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Beare D, et al . COSMIC: mining complete cancer ge- nomes in the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer. Nucleic Acids Res 2011;39:D945-D950.

5.   Huang da W, Sherman BT, Lempicki RA. Systematic and integrative analysis of large gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nat Protoc 2009;4:44-57.

6.   Zeeberg BR, Qin H, Narasimhan S, Sunshine M, Cao H, Kane DW, et al . High-Throughput GoMiner, an 'in- dustrial-strength' integrative gene ontology tool for in- terpretation of multiple-microarray experiments, with ap- plication to studies of Common Variable Immune Defi- ciency (CVID). BMC Bioinformatics 2005;6:168.

7.   Beissbarth T, Speed TP. GOstat: find statistically over- represented Gene Ontologies within a group of genes. Bioinformatics 2004;20:1464-1465.

8.   Khatri P, Voichita C, Kattan K, Ansari N, Khatri A, Georgescu C, et al . Onto-Tools: new additions and im- provements in 2006. Nucleic Acids Res 2007;35:W206-

Cancer Gene Annotator   39

W211.

9. Subramanian A, Tamayo P, Mootha VK, Mukherjee S, Ebert BL, Gillette MA, et al . Gene set enrichment anal- ysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting ge- nome-wide expression profiles. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 2005;102:15545-15550.

10. Ng PC, Henikoff S. SIFT: Predicting amino acid changes that affect protein function. Nucleic Acids Res 2003;31:3812-3814.

11. Adzhubei IA, Schmidt S, Peshkin L, Ramensky VE, Gerasimova A, Bork P, et al . A method and server for predicting damaging missense mutations. Nat Methods 2010;7:248-249.

12. Pleasance ED, Stephens PJ, O'Meara S, McBride DJ, Meynert A, Jones D, et al . A small-cell lung cancer ge- nome with complex signatures of tobacco exposure. Nature 2010;463:184-190.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 7-----------------------------------------------------
