G&I

Genomics & Informatics

eISSN 2234-0742 Genomics Inform 2014;12(4):236-239  ttp://dx.doi.org/10.5808/GI.2014.12.4.236

ORIGINAL ARTICLE

Replication of Interactions between Genome-Wide Genetic Variants and Body Mass Index in Fasting

Glucose and Insulin Levels

Kyung-Won Hong 1 , Myungguen Chung 1,2 , Seong Beom Cho 1 *

1 Division of Biomedical Informatics, Center for Genome Science, National Institute of Health, KCDC, Cheongju 363-951, Korea,

2 Division of Molecular and Life Science, Hanyang University, Seoul 133-791, Korea

The genetic regulation of glucose and insulin levels might be modified by adiposity. With regard to the genetic factors that are altered by adiposity, a large meta-analysis on the interactions between genetic variants and body mass index with regard to fasting glucose and insulin levels was reported by the Meta-Analyses of Glucose- and Insulin-related trait Consortium (MAGIC), based on European ancestry. Because no replication study has been performed in other ethnic groups, we first examined the link between reported single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and fasting glucose and insulin levels in a large Korean cohort (Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study cohort [KoGES], n = 5,814). The MAGIC study reported 7 novel SNPs for fasting glucose levels and 6 novel SNPs for fasting insulin levels. In this study, we attempted to replicate the association of 5 SNPs with fasting glucose levels and 5 SNPs with fasting insulin levels. One SNP (rs2293941) in PDX1 was identified as a significant obesity-modifiable factor in Koreans. Our results indicate that the novel loci that were identified by MAGIC are poorly replicated in other ethnic groups, although we do not know why. Keywords: European, glucose, GWAS, insulin, SNP

BMI with regard to fasting glucose and insulin levels were

Introduction

The rapid socioeconomic developments in developing countries have led to a shift in infrastructure, technology, and food supply, promoting overnutrition and sedentary lifestyles [1]. Consequently, the prevalence of metabolic diseases, such as obesity and type 2 diabetes, has risen dramatically [2, 3]. In particular, Asian countries have experienced a notable increase in metabolic disease; thus, prevention and control of metabolic diseases should be the top public health priorities in Asian populations [3]. Glucose and insulin levels after overnight fasting are important indicators of glucose tolerance, insulin resistance, and type 2 diabetes [4]. Adiposity is believed modulate the

analyzed by the Meta-Analyses of Glucose- and Insulin- related traits Consortium (MAGIC) [6]. MAGIC identified several novel genetic variants: 7 SNPs ( ARAP1 , FOXA2, DPYSL5 , PCSK1 , PDX1 , PPP1R3B , and OR4S1 ) for fasting glucose level and 6 SNPs ( COBLL1-GRB14, IRS1, PPP1R3B, PDGFC, UHRF1BP1, and LYPLAL1 ) for fasting insulin level [6]. The MAGIC study comprised approximately 70,000 nondiabetic individuals of European ancestry, and its results should be confirmed in other ethnic groups [7].

Because no replication study has been performed in other ethnicities, we examined these SNPs and their association with fasting glucose and insulin levels and determined whether they are modified by obesity in the Korean population. The study design can be found in Fig. 1.

genetic determinants of fasting glucose and insulin levels [5]. To identify genetic determinants that could be modified by body mass index (BMI), the interactions between genome-wide single-nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and

Received November 1, 2014; Revised November 24, 2014; Accepted November 24, 2014 * Corresponding author: Tel: +82-43-719-8850, Fax: +82-43-719-8869, E-mail: sbcho@korea.kr

Copyright © 2014 by the Korea Genome Organization

CC It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/).

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Methods

Study subjects and genotypes

The subjects and their genotypes in the original study have been reported [7]. The initial subjects were obtained from a subset of the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study cohort (KoGES), known as Korean Association Re- source (KARE, n = 8,842) [7]. Written informed consent was obtained from all participants, and this project was approved by the institutional review board at Korea National Institute of Health (KNIH).

Phenotypes and quantitative traits

Past diabetes history was obtained through structured questionnaires by interviewers. Anthropometric measure-

Fig. 1. Schematic of the study design. SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism; BMI, body mass index; MAGIC, Meta-Analysis of Glucose and Insulin Consortium; KARE, Korean Association Resource consortium.

Genomics & Informatics Vol. 12, No. 4, 2014

ments, including weight and height, were also obtained, and

BMI was calculated as weight (kg)/height (m 2 ) [2]. Bio-

chemical assessments were performed, including fasting serum glucose, 2-h 75 g oral glucose tolerance test, and fasting serum insulin (FSI). A total of 3,028 subjects with prevalent hyperglycemia (fasting glucose ≥ 110, 2-h glucose level after 75 g oral glucose challenge ≥ 140), or self-reported diabetes history were excluded. Of the 8,842 individuals who were examined in the previous genome- wide association study [7], 5,814 nondiabetic individuals were selected.

SNP genotypes

The genotypes were obtained using the Affymetrix Genome-Wide Human SNP array 5.0 (Affymetrix Inc., Santa Clara, CA, USA). The genotype quality control criteria have been reported in a previous genome-wide association study [7]. Briefly, every 500 ng of genomic DNA was genotyped on the Affy 5.0, and the Bayesian robust linear genotyping algorithm using Mahalanobis distance was used for genotype calling [8]. Samples with a high missing genotype call rate ( ≥ 4 % ), high heterozygosity ( ＞ 30 % ), inconsisten- cy in sex, and any tumor were excluded from subsequent analyses.

Genotype imputation

Of the 13 SNPs that were reported by the MAGIC con- sortium, 4 SNPs were genotyped in the original KARE genotype data using the Affy 5.0. To maximize the validation SNPs in Koreans, the Chinese-Japanese HapMap dataset was imputed to obtain 6 additional SNPs. Thus, 10 SNPs were analyzed in this study. The detailed imputation procedure has been published. Briefly, the KARE dataset, comprising 351,677 SNPs in 8,842 individuals, was merged with that of the international HapMap Phase II Japanese (JPT) + Chinese (HCB) panel 2 [9]. The genotypes of the KARE individuals were imputed using IMPUTE [10]. Using the following filtering scheme — INFO ≥ 0.5 and posterior probability ≥

Table 1. Clinical characteristics

Characteristic                                      Body mass index (BMI) strata

BMI ＜ 20       20 ≤ BMI ＜ 25      25 ≤ BMI ＜ 30      30 ≤ BMI

No.                                       366              3,143               2,068             237 Residential area (Anseong/Ansan)               223/143           1511/1632            964/1,104          131/106 Sex (male/female)                           216/150          1,495/1,648           981/1,087           67/170 Age (y)                                 53.7 ± 10.1        51.0 ± 8.8           50.8 ± 8.3        52.0 ± 8.1

2

Fasting glucose levels (mmol/L)               4.42 ± 0.42        4.52 ± 0.41          4.60 ± 0.42       4.65 ± 0.48 Fasting serum insulin levels (pmol/L)           39.5 ± 17.8        46.8 ± 20.0          57.0 ± 25.2       68.0 ± 30.0 Values are presented as number or mean ± standard deviation.

www.genominfo.org                                               237

Body mass index (kg/m )                   18.9 ± 0.9         22.8 ± 1.3           26.7 ± 1.2        31.6 ± 1.7

-----------------------------------------------------Page 2-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
KW Hong, et al . SNP-BMI Interactions and Glucose and Insulin Levels

0.9 − 1,827,004 SNPs were imputed, and 6 SNPs that matched among the 13 SNPs that were reported by MAGIC were selected for study. Statistical analysis

Glucose and insulin levels were natural log-transformed. To examine the effects of SNP-BMI interactions on them, we conducted 4 statistical tests for each SNP. In all analyses, residential area, age, sex, and BMI were the covariates. The first 2 tests were linear regression analyses of lean (BMI ＜ 25) and overweight subjects (BMI ≥ 25). The overall interactions between SNPs and BMI were analyzed using continuous BMI values and dichotomized BMI (lean subjects were coded with 1, and overweight subjects were coded with 2). Continuous BMI-SNP interaction analyses were perform- ed using QUICKTEST (http://toby.freeshell.org/software/

quicktest.shtml), and the dichotomized BMI-SNP inter- actions were analyzed using PLINK, version 1.07 [11].

Results and Discussion

The fasting serum glucose and insulin levels of our subjects are shown in Table 1. We divided subjects into 4 groups, based on BMI; most Korean subjects lay in the 20 ≤ BMI ＜ 25 and 25 ≤ BMI ＜ 30 categories. The MAGIC study had BMI cutoffs of ＜ 25 and ≥ 30, and 237 of our subjects (4 % ) had BMI ≥ 30. Asians have lower rates of over- weightedness and obesity than Western populations, per conventional definitions (BMI ≥ 25 for overweightedness and ≥ 30 for obesity) [3]. Despite having lower BMIs, Asian countries have a similar or greater prevalence of diabetes versus Western countries [12]. Thus, we used BMI ＜ 25 and

Table 2. Replication results of MAGIC-reported SNPs for fasting insulin levels and fasting glucose levels

Nearest gene

Parameter

Fasting insulin levels                                         Fasting glucose levels

COBLL1-G

RB14       IRS1    PPP1R3B    PDGFC   UHRF1BP1   LYPLAL1    ARAP1    FOXA2    DPYSL5    PCSK1     PDX1    PPP1R3B    OR4S1

MAGIC [6]

SNP       rs7607980   rs2943634 rs4841132   rs4691380 rs4646949   rs2785980 rs11603334 rs6048205 rs1371614 rs13179048 rs2293941   rs4841132 rs1483121 R           T         C         A         C         T         T         G         A         T         C         A         A         G Freq         0.88       0.66       0.10       0.67       0.75       0.67       0.83       0.95       0.25       0.69       0.22       0.10       0.86 BMI < 25

Beta        0.023      0.018      0.021      0.016      0.014      0.016      0.022      0.040      0.020      0.022      0.019      0.027      0.021 SE         0.003      0.003      0.004      0.003      0.003      0.003      0.003      0.005      0.003      0.003      0.003      0.005      0.004

BMI ≥ 30

Beta        0.039      0.025      0.031      0.021      0.020      0.017      0.030      0.029      0.022      0.018      0.016      0.030      0.015 SE         0.004      0.004      0.006      0.004      0.004      0.004      0.004      0.007      0.004      0.004      0.004      0.007      0.005

Joint-meta 4.3 × 10   -20   2.5 × 10 -14   1.7 × 10

analysis

-10   5.3 × 10
 -9   3.7 × 10
 -8   2.0 × 10
 -8   2.4 × 10
 -14   1.6 × 10 -12   2.3 × 10
 -12   1.6 × 10 -10   5.3 × 10
 -10   7.6 × 10
 -9    1.6×10
 -8

p-value

KARE

G/I            -        G         I         G         G         G         I         I           -        I         I         I           - R             -        C         A         C         T         T         G         A           -        C         A         A           - Freq           -        0.92       0.01       0.71       0.41       0.67       0.94       0.85         -        0.70       0.47       0.01         - BMI < 25

Lean          -        3,508 3,503 3,509 3,508      3,507      3,439      3,495        -        3,488      3,485      3,497        - Beta          -        0.001 − 0.017 − 0.010 − 0.015      0.009      0.001      0.008        -      − 0.002      0.007      0.006        - SE           -        0.021 0.047 0.013 0.012      0.013      0.005      0.003        -        0.002      0.002      0.008        -

p-value        -        9.7E-01 7.2E-01 4.6E-01 2.0E-01     4.6E-01     9.1E-01    1.0E-02   a     -       3.7E-01    1.1E-03 b     5.1E-01      -

BMI ≥ 25

Obese        -        2,303 2,303 2,305      2,302      2,305      2,262      2,287        -        2,291      2,290      2,303        - Beta          -        0.004 − 0.013 − 0.009      0.008      0.015      0.005      0.005        -        0.002      0.000      0.017        - SE           -        0.027 0.069 0.016      0.015      0.016      0.005      0.004        -        0.003      0.003      0.013        - p-value        -        8.8E-01 8.5E-01 5.7E-01     5.7E-01    3.5E-01     3.2E-01    1.7E-01      -        5.6E-01     8.7E-01    1.8E-01      -

Interaction

p-value

Continuo

Dichotom

0.88       0.81       0.90       0.11       0.44       0.92       0.87         -        0.60       0.24       0.52         -

0.76       0.97       0.96       0.24       0.71       0.44       0.56         -        0.44       0.04   c      0.73        -

MAGIC, Meta-Analyses of Glucose- and Insulin-related trait Consortium; SNP, single-nucleotide polymorphism; R, trait-rising allele Freq, R allele frequency; BMI, body mass index; SE, standard error of beta; KARE, Korean Association Resource; G/I, genotyped SNP/imputed SNP; the replicated SNPs are in bold; FDR, false discovery rate.

b c

238                                     www.genominfo.org

us BMI       -

ized BMI      -

a Adjusted p-value: FDR = 0.05, Bonferroni = 0.10; FDR = 0.011, Bonferroni = 0.011; FDR = 0.40, Bnferroni = 0.40.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 3-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
BMI ≥ 25 to analyze the effects of SNPs and SNP-dichoto- mized BMI interactions by stratum.

Of the 6 SNPs that were associated with FSI levels in the MAGIC studies, 5 SNPs could be tested in the current study, and no SNP was replicated in all 3 statistical tests (stratified BMI, continuous BMI interaction p-values, and dichoto- mized BMI interaction p-values) (see Table 2). Of the 7 reported SNPs that were linked to fasting plasma glucose levels, 5 SNPs could be tested in the current study, and 1 SNP (rs2293941) in pancreatic and duodenal homeobox 1 ( PDX1 ) was significantly associated in lean subjects (beta ± SE, 0.007 ± 0.002; p = 0.001) but not in overweight subjects. The SNP-continuous BMI interaction was not significant, but the SNP-dichotomized BMI interaction was marginal (p = 0.04).

Our results indicate that the novel loci that were identified by MAGIC are poorly replicated in other ethnic groups, although we do not know why. We have identified an important genetic factor of glucose metabolism, PDX1 , which regulates pancreatic beta-cell function and survival by governing expression of the insulin-encoding INS gene [13]. This study was limited by its exclusion of 3 other SNP-BMI interactions from MAGIC. These SNPs could not be ex- tracted from the imputation data using the original Affy 5.0 in the KARE study. Another limitation of this study was the relatively weak significance of its association results com- pared with those of MAGIC. We do not know whether this lack of significance is due to the relatively smaller sample size of this study compared with MAGIC, the inaccuracy of imputation genotypes, or ethnic differences in the SNP-BMI interactions. These issues should be addressed in other Asian populations.

Although the replication of gene-environment interac- tions in other ethnic groups is difficult, interethnic con- servation of the interaction results might help us determine the underlying mechanisms of the target phenotypes. Further, the rs2293941 SNP might help us understand individual differences in beta-cell function.

Acknowledgments

The genotypes and epidemiological traits were provided with biospecimens and data from the Korean Genome Analysis Project (4845-301, 2013-NG72001-00), the Korean Genome and Epidemiology Study (4851-302), and the

Genomics & Informatics Vol. 12, No. 4, 2014

Korean Biobank Project (4851-307, KBP-2013-000), which were supported by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention, Republic of Korea.

References

1. den Boer AT, Herraets IJ, Stegen J, Roumen C, Corpeleijn E, Schaper NC, et al . Prevention of the metabolic syndrome in IGT subjects in a lifestyle intervention: results from the SLIM study. Nutr Metab Cardiovasc Dis 2013;23:1147-1153.

2. Katzmarzyk PT. Physical activity, sedentary behavior, and health: paradigm paralysis or paradigm shift? Diabetes 2010; 59:2717-2725.

3. Chan JC, Malik V, Jia W, Kadowaki T, Yajnik CS, Yoon KH, et al . Diabetes in Asia: epidemiology, risk factors, and pathophy- siology. JAMA 2009;301:2129-2140.

4. Sims EA, Danforth E Jr. Expenditure and storage of energy in

man. J Clin Invest 1987;79:1019-1025.

5. Kahn SE, Hull RL, Utzschneider KM. Mechanisms linking obesity to insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. Nature 2006; 444:840-846.

6. Manning AK, Hivert MF, Scott RA, Grimsby JL, Bouatia-Naji N, Chen H, et al . A genome-wide approach accounting for body mass index identifies genetic variants influencing fast- ing glycemic traits and insulin resistance. Nat Genet 2012;44: 659-669.

7. Cho YS, Go MJ, Kim YJ, Heo JY, Oh JH, Ban HJ, et al . A large-scale genome-wide association study of Asian pop- ulations uncovers genetic factors influencing eight quantita- tive traits. Nat Genet 2009;41:527-534.

8. Rabbee N, Speed TP. A genotype calling algorithm for affyme-

trix SNP arrays. Bioinformatics 2006;22:7-12.

9. Hong KW, Lim JE, Kim YJ, Cho NH, Shin C, Oh B. KARE ge- nomewide association study of blood pressure using imputed SNPs. Genomics Inform 2010;8:103-107.

10. Howie BN, Donnelly P, Marchini J. A flexible and accurate gen- otype imputation method for the next generation of ge- nome-wide association studies. PLoS Genet 2009;5:e1000529. 11. Purcell S, Neale B, Todd-Brown K, Thomas L, Ferreira MA, Bender D, et al . PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome associa- tion and population-based linkage analyses. Am J Hum Genet 2007;81:559-575.

12. Yoon KH, Lee JH, Kim JW, Cho JH, Choi YH, Ko SH, et al . Epidemic obesity and type 2 diabetes in Asia. Lancet 2006;368: 1681-1688.

13. Macfarlane WM, Frayling TM, Ellard S, Evans JC, Allen LI, Bulman MP, et al . Missense mutations in the insulin promoter factor-1 gene predispose to type 2 diabetes. J Clin Invest 1999;104:R33-R39.

www.genominfo.org                                               239

-----------------------------------------------------Page 4-----------------------------------------------------
