<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GNI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Genomics &amp; Informatics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korea Genome Organization</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25031568</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4099349</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2014.12.2.58</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Association Analysis of <italic>TEC</italic> Polymorphisms with Aspirin-Exacerbated Respiratory Disease in a Korean Population</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lee</surname>
            <given-names>Jin Sol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN3">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Bae</surname>
            <given-names>Joon Seol</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="FN3">&#x2020;</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Byung-Lae</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Cheong</surname>
            <given-names>Hyun Sub</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jeong-Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Jason Yongha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Namgoong</surname>
            <given-names>Suhg</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Kim</surname>
            <given-names>Ji-On</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Park</surname>
            <given-names>Choon-Sik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A5">5</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shin</surname>
            <given-names>Hyoung Doo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A4">4</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="FN2">**</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Research Institute for Basic Science, Sogang University, Seoul 121-742, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Department of Life Science, Sogang University, Seoul 121-742, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Laboratory of Translational Genomics, Samsung Genome Institute, Samsung Medical Center, Seoul 135-710, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A4"><label>4</label>Department of Genetic Epidemiology, SNP Genetics, Inc., Seoul 153-801, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A5"><label>5</label>Division of Allergy and Respiratory Medicine, Soonchunhyang University Seoul Hospital, Seoul 140-743, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="FN1"><sup>*</sup>Corresponding author 1: Tel: +82-32-621-5105, Fax: +82-32-621-5016, <email>schalr@schbc.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <corresp id="FN2"><sup>**</sup>Corresponding author 2: Tel: +82-2-3273-1671, Fax: +82-2-3273-1680, <email>hdshin@sogang.ac.kr</email></corresp>
        <fn id="FN3" fn-type="equal">
          <p><sup>&#x2020;</sup>These two authors contributed equally to this work.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>58</fpage>
      <lpage>63</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>02</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>5</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 by the Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The tyrosine-protein kinase Tec (TEC) is a member of non-receptor tyrosine kinases and has critical roles in cell signaling transmission, calcium mobilization, gene expression, and transformation. TEC is also involved in various immune responses, such as mast cell activation. Therefore, we hypothesized that <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms might be involved in aspirin-exacerbated respiratory disease (AERD) pathogenesis. We genotyped 38 <italic>TEC</italic> single nucleotide polymorphisms in a total of 592 subjects, which comprised 163 AERD cases and 429 aspirin-tolerant asthma controls. Logistic regression analysis was performed to examine the associations between <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and the risk of AERD in a Korean population. The results revealed that <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and major haplotypes were not associated with the risk of AERD. In another regression analysis for the fall rate of forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) by aspirin provocation, two variations (<italic>rs7664091</italic> and <italic>rs12500534</italic>) and one haplotype (<italic>TEC_BL2_ht4</italic>) showed nominal associations with FEV<sub>1</sub> decline (p = 0.03-0.04). However, the association signals were not retained after performing corrections for multiple testing. Despite <italic>TEC</italic> playing an important role in immune responses, the results from the present study suggest that <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms do not affect AERD susceptibility. Findings from the present study might contribute to the genetic etiology of AERD pathogenesis.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>aspirin-exacerbated respiratory disease</kwd>
        <kwd>aspirin-tolerant asthma</kwd>
        <kwd>Tec protein tyrosine kinase</kwd>
        <kwd>genetic polymorphisms</kwd>
        <kwd>haplotypes</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="KR">Korea Health 21 R&amp;D Project</funding-source>
          <award-id>A010249</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="KR">National Research Foundation of Korea</funding-source>
          <award-id>2012-0006690</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Asthma is a disease that is caused by inflammation in the lung and bronchus and is affected by genetic and environmental influences. Aspirin-exacerbated respiratory disease (AERD), which was first reported in 1922, is a type of asthma. AERD is characterized by the following three symptoms: bronchial asthma, aspirin sensitivity, and nasal polyposis [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. It has been reported that 10-20% of asthma patients have aspirin sensitivity, whereas 1-2% of the non-asthma population shows aspirin sensitivity [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. Although the mechanisms of AERD pathogenesis are still not fully understood, inflammatory responses by overproduction of leukotrienes are regarded as the main pathogenesis of AERD.</p>
      <p>Aspirin is a commonly used medication, which belongs to the non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs. Despite being a widely used medication, aspirin intake also causes various side effects, including manifested gastrointestinal ulcer, stomach bleeding, and tinnitus, especially in higher doses. Although the side effects of aspirin are not common, these effects have been reported in about 10% of adult asthmatics. In AERD pathogenesis, aspirin inhibits the activation of cyclooxygenase-1 enzyme, leading to block of production of prostaglandin and thromboxane. This mechanism causes overproduction of leukotrienes, such as leukotriene B4, leukotriene C4, leukotriene D4, and leukotriene E4 [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>, <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>The tyrosine-protein kinase Tec (TEC) is a member of the non-receptor tyrosine kinases and has critical roles in cell signaling transmission, calcium mobilization, gene expression, and transformation [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. It has been known that TEC family kinases are associated with various intracellular signaling mechanisms, such as cytokine receptors and lymphocyte surface antigens [<xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. In particular, it was demonstrated that the TEC family proteins are involved in regulation of leukotriene secretion via the mast cell signaling pathway [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Therefore, we hypothesized that <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms might be involved in AERD pathogenesis. In the present study, 38 <italic>TEC</italic> single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) were genotyped in a total of 592 subjects, which comprised 163 AERD cases and 429 aspirin-tolerant asthma (ATA) controls, to examine the associations between <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and AERD susceptibility.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec>
        <title>Study subjects</title>
        <p>Subjects in this study were recruited from the Asthma Genome Research Center, comprising the hospitals of Soonchunhyang, Chunnam, Chungbuk, Seoul National, and Chung-Ang Universities in Korea. All subjects provided written informed consents, and the study protocols were approved by the institutional review board of each hospital. Diagnosis of AERD was performed according to a modified method as previously described [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. We also performed aspirin challenge in subjects with a history of aspirin hypersensitivity, presence of urticaria, nasal polyp, and sinusitis. The AERD case group included patients with 20% or greater decreases in forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV<sub>1</sub>) or 15% to 19% decreases in FEV<sub>1</sub> with naso-ocular or cutaneous reactions, whereas subjects showing a rate of FEV<sub>1</sub> decline less than 15% without extrabronchial nasal or skin symptoms were included in the ATA group. The clinical diagnostic factors for the present study are summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>SNP selection and genotyping</title>
        <p>To investigate the associations between <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and the risk of AERD, we selected candidate SNPs based on allele frequencies in the Asian population, linkage disequilibrium (LD) status, and National Center for Biotechnology information. The data for selection were obtained from the International HapMap database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hapmap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/">http://hapmap.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</ext-link>). Genotyping of 38 <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms was performed in a total of 592 subjects, including 163 AERD cases and 429 ATA controls. Genotyping was carried out with 20 ng of genomic DNA by TaqMan assay using ABI prism 7900HT sequence detection system software version 2.3 (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA) in all subjects. Assay IDs of all SNPs used in TaqMan assay are listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">Supplementary Table 1</xref>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec>
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p>We applied a widely used measure of linkage disequilibrium to all pairs of biallelic loci: Lewontin's D' (|D'|) [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and r<sup>2</sup>. Haplotypes of each individual were inferred using the PHASE algorithm (ver. 2.0), developed by Stephens et al. [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Linear regression analysis was performed to examine the differences in the rates of decline in FEV<sub>1</sub> following aspirin challenge among the genotypes and major haplotypes. The data were managed and analyzed using Statistical Analysis System, version 9.2 (SAS Inc., Cary, NC, USA). Associations for AERD under the logistic model were adjusted by smoking status, atopy, body mass index (BMI), age, and sex (male = 0, female = 1). Significant associations are shown in boldface (p &lt; 0.05).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <p>We recruited a total of 592 subjects, which consisted of 163 AERD cases and 429 ATA controls, for the present study. According to the results, four clinical characteristics showed significant differences between the case and control groups (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). The fall rate by aspirin provocation was significantly higher in AERD subjects than ATA controls (24.63 &#xB1; 16.11 vs. 3.54 &#xB1; 4.85; p = 0.0001). Percentage of predicted FEV<sub>1</sub> in the AERD subjects showed decreased lung function than in ATA subjects (87.58 &#xB1; 16.94 vs. 91.66 &#xB1; 16.87; p = 0.009). Also, age of first medical examination and BMI were lower in AERD cases than ATA controls. The other diagnostic factors showed no significant differences between the case and control group.</p>
      <p>In the present study, 38 <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and 12 major haplotypes were used for the association analyses. Locations of the polymorphisms are shown in a genetic map of <italic>TEC</italic> with their LD status (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>). Minor allele frequencies (MAFs) of the SNPs in Korean subjects are displayed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">Supplementary Table 2</xref> with their allele change, position, and p-value for Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. All SNPs were in Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. The LD blocks were obtained by using HaploView software, and the haplotypes of each LD block were calculated by PHASE software (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B and 1C</xref>). We used major haplotypes that had frequencies higher than 0.05 for further analyses. The minor haplotypes that had frequencies lower than 0.05 were merged and presented as 'Others.' To compare genetic differences among ethnicities, we obtained MAFs of Caucasians, Han Chinese, Japanese, and Africans from the NCBI database (dbSNP) (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">Supplementary Table 2</xref>) and calculated LD blocks using genotype data from the International HapMap database (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). As a result, Asian populations showed similar MAFs, whereas the other populations showed distinct differences. However, we did not find any correlation in LD status in any ethnicity.</p>
      <p>Logistic analyses were performed to investigate the associations between <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and the risk of AERD. The result from analyses revealed that all SNPs and major haplotypes were not associated with the risk of AERD (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table 2</xref>). On the other hand, two SNPs (<italic>rs7664091</italic>, p = 0.04 and <italic>rs12500534</italic>, p = 0.03) and one major haplotype in LD block 2 (<italic>TEC_BL2_ht4</italic>, p = 0.03) showed marginal associations in the regression analysis with the decline rate of FEV<sub>1</sub> (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">Supplementary Table 3</xref>). However, the association signals of these polymorphisms disappeared after performing corrections for multiple testing (data not shown). Taken together, these results indicate that the <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms are not associated with AERD susceptibility, at least in the Korean population. The lack of associations in this study suggests that although TEC plays an important role in immune responses, <italic>TEC</italic> variants do not directly affect decreased pulmonary function by aspirin uptake. However, considering the fact that the difference in frequency of polymorphisms showed different effects in various populations, replication studies in AERD subjects in other ethnicities are recommended.</p>
      <p>The present study still had several limitations. First, an average statistical power of 66.41% indicated an insufficient sample size. However, the rare condition of AERD made it difficult to recruit subjects in the Korean asthma cohort. Second, SNPs in coding sequence were not selected, due to very low frequencies, although non-synonymous SNPs (nsSNP) in exonic regions could affect risk of the disease. Further studies are required to examine the molecular role of nsSNPs in <italic>TEC</italic>.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, we hypothesized that <italic>TEC</italic> might impact on AERD susceptibility. However, our results showed that 38 <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and 12 major haplotypes were not associated with the risk of AERD. Although further studies are required to investigate the exact role of the <italic>TEC</italic> SNPs in immune responses, the preliminary results of the present study may provide useful information for AERD pathogenesis.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This work was supported by a grant from the Korea Health 21 R&amp;D Project (A010249). This work was supported by a grant from the Priority Research Centers Program through the National Research Foundation of Korea (NRF), funded by the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology (2012-0006690). The DNA samples were generously provided by Soonchunhyang University, Bucheon Hospital Biobank, and a member of the National Biobank of Korea, supported by the Ministry of Health, Welfare and Family Affairs, Republic of Korea.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hur</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sampson</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>CysLTR1 promoter polymorphism and requirement for leukotriene receptor antagonist in aspirin-intolerant asthma patients</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacogenomics</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1143</fpage>
          <lpage>1150</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17924829</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ye</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adenosine deaminase and adenosine receptor polymorphisms in aspirin-intolerant asthma</article-title>
          <source>Respir Med</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>356</fpage>
          <lpage>363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19019667</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Palikhe</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>What do we know about the genetics of aspirin intolerance?</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Pharm Ther</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>465</fpage>
          <lpage>472</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18834360</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Szczeklik</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nizankowska</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duplaga</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Natural history of aspirin-induced asthma. AIANE Investigators. European Network on Aspirin-Induced Asthma</article-title>
          <source>Eur Respir J</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>432</fpage>
          <lpage>436</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11028656</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hedman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaprio</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poussa</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nieminen</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of asthma, aspirin intolerance, nasal polyposis and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in a population-based study</article-title>
          <source>Int J Epidemiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>717</fpage>
          <lpage>722</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10480701</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Funk</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prostaglandins and leukotrienes: advances in eicosanoid biology</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>294</volume>
          <fpage>1871</fpage>
          <lpage>1875</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11729303</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>WC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parekh</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ca2+ influx through CRAC channels activates cytosolic phospholipase A2, leukotriene C4 secretion, and expression of c-fos through ERK-dependent and -independent pathways in mast cells</article-title>
          <source>FASEB J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>2381</fpage>
          <lpage>2383</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023391</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ariyama</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inazawa</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yazaki</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirai</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular cloning and analysis of the human Tec protein-tyrosine kinase</article-title>
          <source>Leukemia</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1663</fpage>
          <lpage>1672</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7934162</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Desiderio</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Human genetics: becoming B cells</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>361</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>203</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7678697</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qiu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kung</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Signaling network of the Btk family kinases</article-title>
          <source>Oncogene</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>5651</fpage>
          <lpage>5661</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11114746</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abramova</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boucheron</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckelhart</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schebesta</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bilic</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The protein tyrosine kinase Tec regulates mast cell function</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Immunol</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>3228</fpage>
          <lpage>3238</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19688741</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Early and late onset asthmatic responses following lysine-aspirin inhalation in aspirin-sensitive asthmatic patients</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Allergy</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7728622</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hedrick</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Gametic disequilibrium measures: proceed with caution</article-title>
          <source>Genetics</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>331</fpage>
          <lpage>341</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3666445</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stephens</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donnelly</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new statistical method for haplotype reconstruction from population data</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>978</fpage>
          <lpage>989</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11254454</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Supplementary materials</title>
      <p>Supplementary data including three tables and one figure can be found with this article online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genominfo.org/src/sm/gni-12-58-s001.pdf">http://www.genominfo.org/src/sm/gni-12-58-s001.pdf</ext-link>.</p>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Table 1</title>
          <p>Assay IDs of 38 single nucleotide polymorphisms in <italic>TEC</italic> gene</p>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gni-12-58-s001.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e966" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Table 2</title>
          <p>Allele distribution of <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms</p>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gni-12-58-s002.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e976" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Table 3</title>
          <p>Regression analysis of <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and haplotypes with the fall rate of FEV<sub>1</sub> by aspirin provocation in a Korean population</p>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gni-12-58-s003.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e989" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
      <supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S4">
        <caption>
          <title>Supplementary Fig. 1</title>
          <p>Linkage disequilibrium (LD) plots for <italic>TEC</italic> gene in five ethnicities. LD plots were calculated by using data from International HapMap Project. (A) LD of Korean. (B) LD of Han Chinese. (C) LD of Japanese. (D) LD of Caucasian. (E) LD of African.</p>
        </caption>
        <media mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf" xlink:href="gni-12-58-s004.pdf" orientation="portrait" id="d35e999" position="anchor"/>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Schematic physical map, haplotypes and linkage disequilibrium (LD) plot of <italic>TEC</italic>. (A) Polymorphisms identified in <italic>TEC</italic>. Coding exons are marked by shaded blocks and untranslated region by white blocks. The LD coefficients (r<sup>2</sup>) are based on the genotypes of Korean samples. (B) Haplotypes are calculated using genotypes of <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms in a Korean population. Only those with frequencies over 0.05 are shown in tables. Haplotypes with frequencies lower than 0.05 are merged into "<italic>Others</italic>." (C) LD coefficients (|D'|) among the selected SNPs based on the genotypes of whole study subjects in this study.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-12-58-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Table 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Clinical profile of subjects in study with <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-12-58-i001"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>Age indicates first medical examination.</p>
          <p>AERD, aspirin-exacerbated respiratory disease; ATA, aspirin-tolerant asthma; BMI, body mass index; FVC, forced vital capacity; FEV<sub>1</sub>, forced expiratory volume in 1 second.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
    <table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Table 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Association analysis of <italic>TEC</italic> polymorphisms and haplotypes with the risk of AERD in a Korean population</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-12-58-i002"/>
      <table-wrap-foot>
        <fn>
          <p>Logistic analyses controlling for age, sex, smoking status, atopy, and body mass index as covariates, performed using the Statistical Analysis System (SAS).</p>
          <p>AERD, aspirin-exacerbated respiratory disease; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism; OR, odds ratio; CI, confidence interval.</p>
        </fn>
      </table-wrap-foot>
    </table-wrap>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>