<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GNI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Genomics &amp; Informatics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Korea Genome Organization</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25705172</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">4330268</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2014.12.4.289</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Application Note</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>MAP: Mutation Arranger for Defining Phenotype-Related Single-Nucleotide Variant</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Baek</surname>
            <given-names>In-Pyo</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jeong</surname>
            <given-names>Yong-Bok</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Jung</surname>
            <given-names>Seung-Hyun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>Yeun-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="A1"><label>1</label>Department of Microbiology, Integrated Research Center for Genome Polymorphism (IRCGP), The Catholic University of Korea College of Medicine, Seoul 137-701, Korea.</aff>
      <aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Quantum Technology, Seongnam 462-807, Korea.</aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp>Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-2258-7343, Fax: +82-2-537-0572, <email>yejun@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>12</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>289</fpage>
      <lpage>292</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2014 by the Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Next-generation sequencing (NGS) is widely used to identify the causative mutations underlying diverse human diseases, including cancers, which can be useful for discovering the diagnostic and therapeutic targets. Currently, a number of single-nucleotide variant (SNV)-calling algorithms are available; however, there is no tool for visualizing the recurrent and phenotype-specific mutations for general researchers. In this study, in order to support defining the recurrent mutations or phenotype-specific mutations from NGS data of a group of cancers with diverse phenotypes, we aimed to develop a user-friendly tool, named mutation arranger for defining phenotype-related SNV (MAP). MAP is a user-friendly program with multiple functions that supports the determination of recurrent or phenotype-specific mutations and provides graphic illustration images to the users. Its operation environment, the Microsoft Windows environment, enables more researchers who cannot operate Linux to define clinically meaningful mutations with NGS data from cancer cohorts.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>mutation</kwd>
        <kwd>next-generation sequencing (NGS)</kwd>
        <kwd>sequence snalysis</kwd>
        <kwd>single-nucleotide variant (SNV)</kwd>
        <kwd>software</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <funding-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="KR">The Ministry for Health, Welfare and Family Affairs</funding-source>
          <award-id>A120175</award-id>
        </award-group>
        <award-group>
          <funding-source country="KR">The Cancer Evolution Research Center project</funding-source>
          <award-id>2012 R1A5A2047939</award-id>
        </award-group>
      </funding-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec sec-type="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>It is widely accepted that mutation is the main causal factor for diverse tumorigenesis [<xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>, <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The recent development of next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies has revolutionized the speed and throughput of DNA sequencing, which facilitates the discovery of new driver mutations [<xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. For example, the <italic>ARID1A</italic> gene is mutated in 83% of gastric cancers with microsatellite instability and the <italic>SF3B1</italic> gene is somatically mutated in 9.7% of chronic lymphocytic leukemia patients [<xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. In colorectal cancers, although the majority of recurrent mutations have been previously known, some novel mutations, such as the mutations in the <italic>SOX9</italic> and <italic>FAM123B</italic> genes, were also identified by NGS technology, which may have implications for colorectal tumorigenesis [<xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In melanoma, approximately 40% was found to have causal mutations affecting B-Raf function [<xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>]. Along with the well-known driver mutations, the novel mutations identified by NGS will be useful for predicting the prognosis and molecular characterization of cancers [<xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Recently, a number of mutation calling tools, such as VarScan [<xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>], Genome Analysis ToolKit [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>], and MuTect [<xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], have been developed to detect single-nucleotide variants (SNVs) or indels from NGS data. However, SNV calling from a single cancer case is not the final step for defining clinically meaningful mutations. To define the pathogenic SNVs in human cancers, a commonly used approach is to identify the phenotype-associated recurrent mutations in the study group. Due to the data size burden of NGS output, profiling the mutations associated with a certain phenotype or prognosis in a study group by a researcher who does not have a bioinformatics background or facilities is very difficult. Currently, there is no user-friendly tool supporting methods for the detection of recurrent or phenotype-specific mutations.</p>
      <p>In this study, in order to support the definition of recurrent mutations or phenotype-specific mutations from NGS data of a group of cancers with diverse phenotypes, we aimed to develop a user-friendly tool, named mutation arranger for defining phenotype-related SNV (MAP).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Description</title>
      <p>MAP software was designed as a standalone program, compatible in Microsoft Windows environments with a user-friendly graphic interface, and compiled codes of MAP can be easily installed. Both Variant Call Format [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and its annotation files, such as ANNOVAR output [<xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], can be used as input files for MAP. When a user loads the input file, called Sample Descriptor file (GSF), MAP software displays the sample set information and filter options (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Once data are loaded, the user can filter the data using the 'Analysis Options' tab in MAP software based on annotation information. By using the sample set and analysis options, MAP software generates the summary metrics for multiple samples. Summary metrics include the mutation status for each sample, total mutation frequency, p-values for differences between phenotype groups based on clinical information, genomic position, reference/observed sequence, and additional information, such as read depth by default. MAP software also displays more detailed information in summary metrics based on the user-selected 'Analysis Options.' In the 'Analysis Result' tab, MAP software provides the frequency- or p-value-based filter function. This functionality supports detection of the recurrent mutations in study subjects and identification of the phenotype-specific mutation that occurs significantly in a certain phenotypic subclass. Then, MAP software represents the user-selected mutations graphically in the 'Visualization' tab. To sort the variants by genomic position, p-value, or frequency, users can use the sort function in the 'Analysis Result' tab. Details of the program download, installation, and analysis procedures are available in the user manual.</p>
      <p>The major steps of MAP are as follows.
<list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>- Generating mutation summary metrics in study subjects</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Determination of recurrent mutations by frequency</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Determination of phenotype-specific mutations by association test</p></list-item><list-item><p>- Graphical illustration of user-selected mutations</p></list-item></list>
</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <p>Mutation calling files from Genome Analysis ToolKit [<xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] can be used directly as input files for 'Sample Descriptor.' Alternatively, manually prepared standard Variant Call Format [<xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] is also available. Annotation information files, such as ANNOVAR outputs, can be used as input files for Sample Descriptor. GSF is a comma-separated values text file that describes the input files, such as GATK output files and ANNOVAR output files, and phenotype information. MAP imports this Sample Descriptor file as the input file. Details are available in the user manual.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Generation of summary metrics </title>
      <p>When users load the input file, MAP software displays the sample set information and filter options in the 'Source' tab. If any file is not prepared properly, MAP software informs the user in the 'Sample Set Files' tab. After data are loaded, the user can filter the data using the 'Analysis Option' tab based on annotation information. MAP software supports eight filter options for exonic function. By using the mutation calls of each sample, MAP generates the summary metrics (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>). Based on user-selected filters in the 'Analysis Options' tab, summary metrics represent additional annotation information, such as gene name, function, known variant, and amino acid change. The additional annotations can be hidden using the SNP filter option in the 'Analysis Option' tab. These mutation metrics are exported into a comma-separated values text file for further investigation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Determination of recurrent or phenotype-specific mutations </title>
      <p>In the 'Analysis Result' tab, MAP software defines the recurrent mutations in study subjects by frequency. The frequency threshold can be determined arbitrarily by the user in the 'Frequency Filter' function. MAP also defines the phenotype-specific mutations using the mutation metrics and phenotype information. Phenotype-specific mutations that occur more frequently in one of two clinical conditions (e.g., drug-responder vs. non-responder) are determined by chi-square test under the user-defined significance level.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec>
      <title>Visualization </title>
      <p>The graphic user interface is implemented in the software for users to easily handle large-scale data or access the analysis result (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B and 2C</xref>). The recurrent or phenotype-specific mutations can also be demonstrated visually in heat-map style. Furthermore, MAP software can support the visualization for additional information at a time. For example, the left and right of the heat-map represent the sample name and mutational spectrum, respectively. The bottom of the heat-map represents the gene name by color for mutational spectrum. Frequency or p-value plots are represented on top of the heat-map (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B and 2C</xref>). This graphical result can be exported into an image file for further investigation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="conclusions">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>MAP is a user-friendly program with multiple functions that supports the determination of recurrent or phenotype-specific mutations and provides graphic illustration images to the users. Its operation environment, Microsoft Windows, enables more researchers who cannot operate Linux to define clinically meaningful mutations with NGS data from cancer cohorts.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgments</title>
      <p>This research was supported by a grant from the KRIBB Research Initiative Program. This study was supported by a grant from the Ministry for Health, Welfare and Family Affairs (A120175) and from the Cancer Evolution Research Center project (2012 R1A5A2047939).</p>
    </ack>
    <fn-group>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p><bold>Availability:</bold> The MAP installation package with an online manual is available at the website <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ircgp.com/MAP/index.html">http://www.ircgp.com/MAP/index.html</ext-link>.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn fn-type="other">
        <p>This is 2014 KOBIC best paper awarded.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
    <ref-list>
      <ref id="B1">
        <label>1</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hanahan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinberg</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hallmarks of cancer: the next generation</article-title>
          <source>Cell</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>144</volume>
          <fpage>646</fpage>
          <lpage>674</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21376230</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B2">
        <label>2</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stadler</surname>
              <given-names>ZK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schrader</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vijai</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robson</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Offit</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cancer genomics and inherited risk</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>687</fpage>
          <lpage>698</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24449244</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B3">
        <label>3</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kahvejian</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quackenbush</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>What would you do if you could sequence everything?</article-title>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1125</fpage>
          <lpage>1133</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18846086</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B4">
        <label>4</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuen</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shi</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chu</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Law</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exome sequencing identifies frequent mutation of <italic>ARID1A</italic> in molecular subtypes of gastric cancer</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>1219</fpage>
          <lpage>1223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22037554</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B5">
        <label>5</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quesada</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Conde</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villamor</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ordonez</surname>
              <given-names>GR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jares</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bassaganyas</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exome sequencing identifies recurrent mutations of the splicing factor <italic>SF3B1</italic> gene in chronic lymphocytic leukemia</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2012</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>47</fpage>
          <lpage>52</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22158541</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B6">
        <label>6</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chung</surname>
              <given-names>YJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical applications of next-generation sequencing in colorectal cancers</article-title>
          <source>World J Gastroenterol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>6784</fpage>
          <lpage>6793</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24187453</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B7">
        <label>7</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davies</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samuels</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of the genome to personalize therapy for melanoma</article-title>
          <source>Oncogene</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>5545</fpage>
          <lpage>5555</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20697348</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B8">
        <label>8</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kovtun</surname>
              <given-names>IV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cheville</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarei</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kosari</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lineage relationship of Gleason patterns in Gleason score 7 prostate cancer</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Res</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>73</volume>
          <fpage>3275</fpage>
          <lpage>3284</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23695551</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B9">
        <label>9</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Javle</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rashid</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Churi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zuo</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eterovic</surname>
              <given-names>AK</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular characterization of gallbladder cancer using somatic mutation profiling</article-title>
          <source>Hum Pathol</source>
          <year>2014</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>701</fpage>
          <lpage>708</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24508317</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B10">
        <label>10</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koboldt</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wylie</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Larson</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLellan</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mardis</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>VarScan: variant detection in massively parallel sequencing of individual and pooled samples</article-title>
          <source>Bioinformatics</source>
          <year>2009</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>2283</fpage>
          <lpage>2285</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19542151</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B11">
        <label>11</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DePristo</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Banks</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poplin</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garimella</surname>
              <given-names>KV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maguire</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartl</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using next-generation DNA sequencing data</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>491</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21478889</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B12">
        <label>12</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cibulskis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lawrence</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carter</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sivachenko</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaffe</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sougnez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensitive detection of somatic point mutations in impure and heterogeneous cancer samples</article-title>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>2013</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>213</fpage>
          <lpage>219</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23396013</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B13">
        <label>13</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="webpage">
          <collab>1000 Genomes</collab>
          <source>VCF (variant call format) version 4.0. 1000 Genomes</source>
          <year>2011</year>
          <date-in-citation content-type="access-date">Accessed 2014 Nov 1</date-in-citation>
          <comment>Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.1000genomes.org/wiki/Analysis/vcf4.0">http://www.1000genomes.org/wiki/Analysis/vcf4.0</ext-link></comment>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="B14">
        <label>14</label>
        <element-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hakonarson</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ANNOVAR: functional annotation of genetic variants from high-throughput sequencing data</article-title>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>2010</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>e164</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20601685</pub-id>
        </element-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
  <floats-group>
    <fig id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 1</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Screenshot of source tab in MAP software. Once data are loaded, the Sample Set Files panel and Analysis Options panel are displayed in the Source tab. In the Sample Set Files tab, MAP software displays the input file status and phenotype information. MAP software supports the filter function in the Analysis Options tab based on annotation information. Examples of the Sample Set Files tab and Analysis Options tab are shown in red and blue boxes, respectively. MAP, mutation arranger for defining phenotype-related single-nucleotide variant.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-12-289-g001"/>
    </fig>
    <fig id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float">
      <label>Fig. 2</label>
      <caption>
        <p>Examples of MAP software output. MAP software generates the summary metrics and graphical illustration of user-selected mutations. (A) Example of summary metrics. Summary metrics include mutation status for each sample, total mutation frequency, p-values for differences between phenotype groups based on clinical information, genomic position, reference/observed sequence, and additional information, such as read depth by default. (B, C) Examples of frequency (B)- and p-value (C)-based visualization, respectively. The left and right of the heat-map represent the sample name and mutational spectrum, respectively. The bottom of the heat-map represents the gene name by color for the mutational spectrum. Frequency or p-value plots are represented on top of the heat-map. MAP, mutation arranger for defining phenotype-related single-nucleotide variant.</p>
      </caption>
      <graphic xlink:href="gni-12-289-g002"/>
    </fig>
  </floats-group>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>