<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Genomics Inform</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">GI</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Genomics &amp; Informatics</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1598-866X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">2234-0742</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Society of Gastrointestinal Intervention</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">30309201</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">6187818</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5808/GI.2018.16.3.43</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">gi-2018-16-3-43</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Editorial</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Editor&#x2019;s Introduction to This Issue (G&amp;I 16:3, 2018)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Chung</surname>
            <given-names>Yeun-Jun</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref rid="c1-gi-2018-16-3-43" ref-type="corresp">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="af1-gi-2018-16-3-43">Precision Medicine Research Center, College of Medicine, The Catholic University of Korea, Seoul 06591, <country>Korea</country></aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="c1-gi-2018-16-3-43"><label>*</label>Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-2258-7343, Fax: +82-2-537-0572, E-mail: <email>yejun@catholic.ac.kr</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2018</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>16</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>43</fpage>
      <lpage>43</lpage>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>Copyright &#xA9; 2018 by the Korea Genome Organization</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2018</copyright-year>
        <license>
          <license-p>It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The identification of prognostic indicators is one of the fundamentally important issues in the management of cancer. In terms of mutational burden, prostate cancer is relatively silent, and the therapeutic options for it, including targeted therapy, are relatively limited. Androgen deprivation therapy is an important therapeutic option for prostate cancer; however, a substantial proportion of prostate cancers progress into castration-resistant prostate cancer, which does not respond to androgen deprivation therapy. In this issue, Dr. Seon-Young Kim&#x2019;s group reports whole-genome sequence data from four pairs of primary prostate cancer and castration-resistant prostate cancer samples. In addition to their scientific exploration, they have released this dataset for the research community as a resource for further understanding the progression of castration-resistant prostate cancer. Dr. In-Jin Jang&#x2019;s group has reported a case study of how pharmacogenomics and pharmacometabolomics can be used to characterize safety and pharmacokinetic profiles in early-phase new drug development clinical trials. Their data support that integrated multi-omics analysis can be useful for elucidating the various characteristics of new drug candidates in early-phase clinical trials. The other papers regard a chemoinformatics approach for the antibacterial evaluation of fluoroquinolones, a genome-wide association study analysis of pork quality, and a text corpus system for G&amp;I, termed GNI Corpus version 1.0, all of which are interesting and useful for genomic research.</p>
    <p>For further details, please visit the G&amp;I homepage (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://genominfo.org">https://genominfo.org</ext-link>).</p>
  </body>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>