G&I

EDITORIAL

Genomics & Informatics

pISSN 1598-866X eISSN 2234-0742

Genomics & Informatics Vol. 10, No. 4, 2012

Genomics Inform 2013;11(4):163  ttp://dx.doi.org/10.5808/GI.2013.11.4.163

Editor’s Introduction to This Issue

Sangsoo Kim*

School of Systems Biomedical Science, Soongsil University, Seoul 156-743, Korea

Earlier issues in this year have focused on the theme of epigenomics. This issue starts with a review on the interplay between epigenetics and cancer genetics, which is followed by two review articles on cancer genomics. One of the pri- mary goals of cancer genomics is to translate its discovery to clinical practice. Subsequent review articles provide per- spectives on clinical informatics and methods on how to prioritize disease-related genes from next-generation se- quencing data. Genome-wide data should be interpreted in the context of systems biology, and the following review articles offers comprehensive information on network bio-
 logy and its applications. The next two review articles handle often overlooked but essential components of genomics, i.e., biobanks and ethical standards. We have two additional reviews, totaling 10.

A couple of original research articles also address cancer genomics. The remaining five articles and an application note cover a wide range of genomics and informatics. In this issue, we have five articles in total that have been con- tributed from outside of Korea. We hope that Genomics & Informatics will advance next year to become a truly inter- national journal that is authored and read worldwide.

* Corresponding author: Tel: +82-2-820-0457, Fax: +82-2-824-4383, E-mail: sskimb@ssu.ac.kr

Copyright © 2013 by the Korea Genome Organization

CC It is identical to the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/).

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
