APPLICATION

NOTE

Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 133-136, September 2007

GSnet: An Integrated Tool for Gene Set Analysis and Visualization

Yoon Jeong ChoP, Hyun Goo Woo^ and Ungsik Yu’*

'Nano Materials Simulation and Fabrication Laboratory, Department of Materials Science and Engineering, KAIST, 373-1 Guseong-dong, Yuseong-gu, Daejeon 305-701, Korea, ^Laboratory of Experimental Carcinogenesis, National Cancer Institute, NIH, USA ^Korean BioInformation Center, Korea Research Institute of Bioscience and Biotechnology, Daejeon 305-806, Korea

Abstract

The Gene Set network viewer (GSnet) visualizes the functional enrichment of a given gene set with a protein interaction network and is implemented as a plug-in for the Cytoscape platform. The functional enrichment of a given gene set is calculated using a hypergeometric test based on the Gene Ontology annotation. The protein interaction network is estimated using public data. Set operations

allow a complex protein interaction network to be decomposed into a functionally-enriched module of interest. GSnet provides a new framework for gene set

analysis by integrating a priori knowledge of a biological network with functional enrichment analysis.

Atrai/ab/ffiy: GSnet is freely available at http://www.kobic. re. kr/gsnet( con/acT yjchoi@kribb.re.kr)

Si/pp/e/nenfa/y/a/b/TnaAbn.'http://www.kobic.re.kr/gsnet

Keywords: microarray analysis, gene set analysis, protein¬

protein interaction network, network visualization

High-throughput data from microarray experiments provide

information about the expression of genes, with gene sets being defined based on the presence of coexpression in these experiments. Several methods have been proposed for the functional analysis of gene sets, including the chi-square test, the hypergeometric test, and the Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) (Boyle etal., 2004; Curtis et al., 2005; Subramanian etal., 2005). These methods find which given gene sets are significantly associated with a priori knowledge data, such as the Gene Ontology (GO) classification (Ashburner et al., 2000), measure the

‘Corresponding author; E-mail ungsik@kribb.re.kr

Tel +82-42-879-8520, Fax +82-42-879-8519 Accepted 28 August 2007

statistical enrichment of genes in a gene set by calculating the p-value using a statistical method, and produce more robust and interpretable information from microarray analyses (Bammler et al., 2005). However, the current state- of-the-art ontological analysis is subject to conceptual limitations (Khatri and Draghid, 2005), and the key regulators

of a gene set can not be elucidated from expression profile alone. The proteinprotein interaction network is a type of scale-free architecture that follows a power-law distribution (Jeong et al., 2001). These scale-free networks are characterized by the existence of hubs with multiple interacting partners, with the genes in the hubs playing a functional key role in maintaining cell functions (Jeong et al., 2001). It is important to understand the relationships and topology of gene expression in the complex hierarchical web of protein interactions (Jeong ef al., 2001; Nikolsky etal., 2005; Rhodes and Chinnaiyan, 2005). Moreover, the presence of coexpression in multiple data sets is indicative of functional relatedness (Lee etal., 2004), which implies

that hub genes in functionally-clustered modules are

functionally significant and worthy of investigation. However,

to the best of our knowledge, there is no available tool that can integrate the functional analyses with analyses of proteinprotein interaction networks. The Gene Set net¬ work viewer (GSnet) has been designed to provide an analytical framework for integrating gene set enrichment analysis with the analysis of proteinprotein interaction

networks. GSnet characterizes and visualizes functional enrichment with the properties of an interaction network. It analyzes the GO term enrichment in a given gene set,

and then constructs a proteinprotein interaction network of the gene set. Furthermore, set operations can be used in GSnet to select interesting genes included in a particular enriched GO term on the network graph in user-defined colors. Our approach facilitates the selection of putative target genes that have functional importance in a given gene set.

GSnet has been developed as a plug-in for Cytoscape, which is an open-source bioinformatics software platform for visualizing molecular interaction networks (available at

http://www.cytoscape.org) (Shannon etal., 2003). GSnet

is freely available at http;//www.kobic.re.kr/gsnet. GSnet

takes a list or a file of Entrez Gene IDs or symbols, and also

supports the two-input-set mode for the analysis of upregulated and downregulated gene sets. GSnet currently supports two protein-protein interaction databases for four species: human, mouse, rat, and yeast. These databases

-----------------------------------------------------Page 1-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
134 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 133-136, September 2007

are generated from the Biomolecular Interaction Network Database (Alfarano ef al., 2005) and the Agilent literature search engine (Agilent Technologies, 2005 http://www. agilent.com/labs/research/mtl/projects/sysbio/sysinfor

matics/litsearch.html) using PubMed (Wheeler et al.,

2005) as a literature reference. For the GO functional enrichment analysis of the gene set, we adopted a hypergeometric test (Tavazoie et al., 1999), which is one of the most widely-used methods. The hypergeometric test calculates the cumulative probability (p-value) of a given specific number of genes from a single gene set in a whole gene list with the hypergeometric distribution. For the correction of the significance of multiple testing, the false discovery rate (FDR) of the Benjamini-Hochberg method (Benjamini and Hochberg, 1995) is also calculated. GSnet provides options for filtering out some enriched functions, including the cut-off p-value, the number of genes within a GO term, and the levels of the GO-term hierarchy. The filtered GO terms are then categorized into molecular function, biological process, and cellular component. The categorized results are displayed in order of ascending

p-value as a tabbed-table in a results window, with two such windows being shown in the two-input-set mode. The

proteinprotein interaction network of given genes is constructed simultaneously using the protein interaction database and visualized in Cytoscape. To customize the

visualization of sub-networks or modules, users can

highlight them by selecting the GO function of interest with

a user-defined color. A set with more than onefunction of interest can be defined by set operations, which allow users to decompose the network and refine functional modules of interest, as shown in Fig. 1. Set operations can be carried out among genes of GO terms in the same or

different GO categories. The set of nodes is selected by checking the "Set A" or "Set B" checkbox beside a GO term, and the type of set operation is specified by marking the appropriate checkbox in the view-option. The selected nodes (i.e., proteins) can be further manipulated to create a child network or to merge them into another network using

the layout functionality supported by Cytoscape. To

identify the hub genes in a given network, GSnet also provides the number of interacting partners of each gene

as a new attribute—the number of edges. Attribute information is shown on the node attribute browser of

Cytoscape. We briefly summarize some specific aspects

of GSnet in Table 1.

File Edit Owi Stieo Layeid Vtsu^izeuon Ruglns CyioP^utelt

Resuii: HYPERCEOMETfUC.P (oa-OfT: Q.05>

, MoleeularFumtidn Ce8u)irCo«f»n«M ) ,

View OntlQit

Help Fibers

11

Select Oenes in input bst A weth color

Seteci Qenes in Set A moa cotor

□ 1 Settci oenes in Set S’olih color

(f 1 Select ®enet in Set (4 m 6> WiA eoJor

I

I 1 1 Select gene? in Set (A n 6) Wih go:or

g« 	 I 1 Select genes in (input Ust a n Jet t» n e» wtn c

Updttie NEtworKView

<1

( Notks- 446 {21 setecteco 1269 O selected!

C^oPanel 2

NoiJo Atuibtrte CiQWser

Sotea ^uWutes i Cre<^ Ne«^ Anribuie

■CF’K

t3c2743

'echl

126129

11003 1C91

etouBhrr rt/flip* «

aF ~

33 10

Node Aunmne Orotascr Edj^Anriindetrowur

Fig. 1. An example GSnef results window and network view in Cytoscape. Nodes in the G0:0006629 term are shown in green and nodes both in G0:0006629 and the input list are shown in red.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 2-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
Gene Set Network Viewer 135

Table 1. Summary of GSnet tool

Function Short description

GSnet is an integrated viewer for analyzing biological networks and the functional enrichment of gene sets. The integration of data derived from heterogeneous experimental sources may help to reduce the influence of noise inherent in experimental data. In addition, putative targets for further studies can be estimated by targeting the hub genes. GSnet can incorporate additional statistical models and databases as needed. We consider GSnet to be a valuable tool that provides a new analytical framework for expanding the interpretation of gene sets and biological networks.

Acknowledgments

The authors thank all members of the Cytoscape deve¬ lopment team. This project was supported by the Korean Ministry of Science & Technology (MoST) under grant number Ml052900001005N290001000.

References

Alfarano, C., Andrade, C.E., Anthony, K., Bahroos, N., Bajec, M., Bantoft, K., Betel, D., Bobechko, B., Boutilier, K., Burgess, E., Buzadzija, K., Cavero, R., D'Abreo, C., Donaldson, I., Dorairajoo, D., Dumontier, M.J., Dumontier, M.R., Earles, V., Farrall, R., Feldman, H., Garderman, E., Gong, Y., Gonzaga, R., Grytsan, V., Gryz, E., Gu, V., Haldorsen, E., Halupa, A., Haw, R., Hrvojic. A., Hurrell, L., Isserlin, R., Jack, F., Juma, F., Khan, A., Kon, T., Konopinsky, S., Le, V., Lee, E., Ling, S., Magidin, M., Moniakis, J., Montojo, J., Moore, S., Muskat, B., Ng, L, Paraiso, J.P., Parker, B., Pintilie, G., Pirone, R., Salama, J. J., Sgro, S., Shan, T., Shu, Y., Siew, J., Skinner, D., Snyder, K., Stasiuk, R., Strumpf, D., Tuekam, B., Tao, S., Wang, Z., White, M., Willis, R., Wolfing, C., Wong, S., Wrong, A., Xin, C., Yao, R., Yates, B., Zhang, S., Zheng,

K. , Pawson, T., Ouellette, B.F., and Hogue, C.W. (2005). The Biomolecular Interaction Network Database and related

tools 2005 update. Nucleic Acids Res. 33, D418-D424

Ashburner, M., Ball, C.A., Blake, J.A., Botstein, D., Butler, H., Cherry, J.M., Davis, A.P., Dolinski, K, Dwight, S.S., Eppig, J.T., Harris, M.A., Hill, D.P., Issel-Tarver, L., Kasarskis, A., Lewis, S., Matese, J.C., Richardson, J.E., Ringwald, M., Rubin, G.M., and Sherlock, G. (2000). Gene Ontology: tool for the unification of biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium. Nat. Genet. 25, 25-29.

Bammler, T., Beyer, R.P., Bhattacharya, S., Boorman, G.A., Boyles, A., Bradford, B.U., Bumgarner, R.E., Bushel, P.R., Chaturvedi, K., Choi, D., Cunningham, M.L., Deng, S., Dressman, H.K., Fannin, R.D., Farin, F.M., Freedman, J.H., Fry, R.C., Harper, A., Humble, M.C., Hurban, P., Kavanagh, T.J., Kaufmann, W.K., Kerr, K.F., Jing, L., Lapidus, J.A., Lasarev, M.R., Li. J,, Li, Y.J., Lobenhofer, E.K., Lu, X., Malek, R.L., Milton, S., Nagalla, S.R., O'malley, J.P., Palmer, V.S., Pattee, P., Paules, R.S., Perou, C.M., Phillips, K., Qin, L.X., Qiu, Y., Quigley, S.D., Rodland, M., Rusyn, I., Samson, L.D., Schwartz, D.A., Shi, Y., Shin, J.L., Sieber, S.O., Slifer, S., Speer, M.C., Spencer, P.S., Sproles, D.I., Swenberg, J.A., Suk, W.A., Sullivan, R.C., Tian, R., Tennant, R.W., Todd, S.A., Tucker, C.J., Van Houten,B., Weis, B.K., Xuan, S., ZarbI, H. Members of the Toxicogenomics Research Consortium.

(2005). Standardizing global gene expression analysis

between laboratories and across platforms. Nat. Methods

2, 351-356.

Benjamin!, Y. and Hochberg, Y. (1995). Controlling the false discovery rate: A practical and powerful approach to multiple testing. J. R. Stati. Soc. B. 57, 280-300.

Boyle, E.I., Weng, S., Gollub, J., Jin, H., Botstein, D., Cherry, J.M., and Sherlock, G. (2004). GO::TermFinderopen

source software for accessing Gene Ontology information and finding significantly enriched Gene Ontology terms

associated with a list of genes Bioinforrmtics 20,3710-3715.

Curtis, R.K., Oresic, M., and Vidal-Puig, A. (2005). Pathways to the analysis of microarray data. Trends Biotechnol. 23, 429-435.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 3-----------------------------------------------------
﻿
136 Genomics & Informatics Vol. 5(3) 133-136, September 2007

Jeong, H., Mason, S.P., Barabasi, A.-L., and Oltvai, Z.N. (2001). Lethality and centrality in protein networks. Nature 411,41-42.

Khatri, P. andDraghici, S. (2005). Ontological analysis of gene expression data: current tools, limitations, and open problems. Bioinformatics 21, 3587-3595.

Lee, H.K., Hsu, A. K., Sajdak, J., Qin, J., and Pavlidis, P. (2004). Co-expression analysis of human genes across many microarray data sets. Genome Res. 14, 1085-94.

Nikolsky, Y., Nikolskaya, T., and Bugrim, A. (2005). Biological networks and analysis of experimental data in drug discovery. Drug Discov. Today 10, 653-662.

Rhodes, D.R. and Chinnaiyan, AM. (2005).lntegrative analysis

of the cancer transcriptome. Nat. Genet. 37,S31-S37.

Shannon, P., Markiel, A., Ozier, O., Baliga, N.S., Wang, J.T., Ramage, D., Amin, N., Schwikowski, B., and Ideker, T. (2003). Cytoscape: a software environment for integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome Research 13, 2498-2504.

Subramanian, A., Tamayo, P., Mootha, V.K., Mukherjee, S.,

Ebert, B.L., Gillette, M.A., Paulovich, A., Pomeroy, S.L., Golub, T.R., Lander, E.S., and Mesirov, J.P. (2005). Gene set enrichment analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proc. Natl

Acad. Sci. 102, 15545-15550.

Tavazoie, S., Hughes, J.D., Campbell, M.J., Cho, R.J., andChurch., G.M. (1999). Systematic determination of genetic network architecture. Nat. Genet. 22, 281-285. Wheeler, D.L., Barrett, T., Benson, D.A., Bryant, S.H., Canese, K., Church, D.M., DiCuccio, M., Edgar, R., Federhen, S., Helmberg, W., Kenton, D.L., Khovayko, O., Lipman, D.J., Madden, T.L., Maglott, D.R., Ostell, J., Pontius, J.U., Pruitt, K.D., Schuler, G.D., Schriml, L.M., Sequeira, E., Sherry, S.T., Sirotkin, K., Starchenko, G., Suzek, T.O., Tatusov, R., Tatusova, T.A., Wagner, L., and

Vaschenko, E.. (2005). Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology Information. Nucleic

Acids Res. 33, D39-D45.

-----------------------------------------------------Page 4-----------------------------------------------------
